<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Information Interfaces And Presentation</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Related Work The Visual Analytics</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>International Workshop on Visual Analytics (2011) S Miksch and G Santucci (Editors) Understanding the Role and Value of Interaction: First Steps W Aigner Institute of Software Technology &amp; Interactive Systems</term>
					<term>Vienna University of Technology</term>
					<term>Austria Department of Information and Knowledge Engineering</term>
					<term>Danube University Krems</term>
					<term>Austria</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Visual Analytics strongly emphasizes the importance of interaction. However, until now, interaction is only sparingly treated as subject matter on its own. How and why interactivity is beneficial to gain insight and make decisions is mostly left in the dark. Due to this lack of initial direction, it seems important to make further attempts in facilitating a deeper understanding of the concept of interactivity. Therefore, different perspectives towards interactivity are discussed and cognitive theories and models are investigated. The main aim of this paper is to broaden the view on interaction and spark further discussion towards a sound theoretical grounding for the field. Categories and Subject Descriptors (according to community is consistently stating the value and importance of interaction for visual data analysis. Despite this, empirical studies or theoretical models that support these statements are scarce or missing at all. Until now the value of interaction has largely been treated as a minor issue in empirical studies. Nevertheless, it has mainly been promoted by experts as valuable asset. &quot;Interactivity&quot; and &quot;interaction&quot; are often used terms but concise definitions are hardly ever given. From the perspective of media, we might say that a paper map is static. But what if we cut and fold the paper map? Isn&apos;t that also interaction? And what if we use a paper map to find a certain street? We are obviously interacting with the world but where does the interactivity re-side? In our tools? In us human beings? Albeit it sounds easy to define interactivity, the concept quickly becomes blurry. VA experts state that interactivity is a powerful concept that enables us to improve analytical reasoning in many ways. Studies like [SNLD06] also provide some evidence for this but research on describing why and how this is the case and the mechanisms behind it, is largely missing. As Liu et al. mention, &quot;the field still lacks supporting, encompassing the-ories&quot; [LNS08]. Therefore, they call for cognitive theories and models as the basis for research. This approach shall be picked up in this paper: First, we will discuss the concept of interactivity and its different facets. Second, cognitive theories and models will be investigated. The aim of this paper is to present different views on interaction and contribute to the research towards a science of interaction. In the research and development agenda for VA [TC05] it</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Interactivity</head><p>In order to be able to grasp the concept of interactivity, we follow the path of Stromer-Galley <ref type="bibr">[Str04]</ref> who argues that we have to tackle interactivity from two perspectives - interactivity-as-product and interactivity-as-process. In the first view, interactivity is seen as a property of the medium itself, whereas in the second, interactivity is conceptualized as intangible concept of a process. These two views shall be used as starting points for further investigation.</p><p>of users with the data. Therefore, also the user's tasks, goals as well as the interaction context are taken into considera- tion. The use of tools is deeply rooted in human development and even precedes the use of language <ref type="bibr">[KN06]</ref>. Postcogni- tivist theories mainly follow this approach and focus on the process of interaction itself -activities of people using tech- nology. In traditional HCI, the more narrow view of user- system interaction is taken. While this attempt is much richer with regard to including aspects related to users, the interac- tivity of artifacts themselves is not an issue. In this sense, also the process of visual perception can be considered as interaction with the environment. Visual perception itself is a dynamic process and does not work just like a digital cam- era. Quite on the contrary, visual perception is a highly dy- namic process that is determined by many internal factors such as attention, focus, or experience <ref type="bibr">[War04]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Interactivity-as-Product</head><p>In the tradition of VA, interactivity is often seen as a property of the tool in terms of the elements offered for user interac- tion. According to Spence, " <ref type="bibr">[i]</ref>nteraction between human and computer is at the heart of modern information visu- alization and for a single overriding reason: the enormous benefit that can accrue from being able to change one's view of a corpus of data" <ref type="bibr">[Spe07]</ref>. However, while the benefits of being able to change one's view are often stated, there is hardly ever an explanation of what these benefits actually are as well as how and why they work. Of particular im- portance is the interaction style of direct manipulation. Ac- cording to <ref type="bibr">[HHN85]</ref>, a major point of importance of direct manipulation is the fact that it gives a feeling of directness of manipulation. Reducing the information processing distance between the user's intentions and the facilities provided by the machine, makes the interface feel more direct by reduc- ing the effort required by the user to accomplish goals. It is assumed that this feeling of directness results from the com- mitment to fewer cognitive resources <ref type="bibr">[HHN85]</ref>. From a cog- nitive point of view, there are two main aspects of directness -distance and engagement. Norman <ref type="bibr">[Nor88]</ref> describes two types of distances, which he termed gulf of execution and gulf of evaluation, which are part of his execution-evaluation cycle. Direct manipulation helps to bridge these gaps with less effort. Engagement, the second main aspect of direct manipulation, refers to "a feeling of first-personness, of di- rect engagement with the objects that concern us" <ref type="bibr">[HHN85]</ref>. This provides a feeling of control that is generally perceived positively in contrast to communication with an intermedi- ary. Interactivity is not simply a yes/no property of a tool or medium, but there are different degrees of interactivity which are determined by the extent to which a user can par- ticipate in modifying the visual representation <ref type="bibr">[Ste92]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">The Value of Interactivity?</head><p>Apart from investigating how interaction techniques work and how interactivity can be modeled, it is important to ex- amine what users actually achieve by using interaction tech- niques <ref type="bibr">[LNS08]</ref>. This is a question that is quite hard to an- swer. One possible explanation of the advantage of interac- tivity is, that it reduces the cognitive load by enhancing the expressiveness of the interface language (possible inputs and outputs) and minimizing the gulfs of execution and evalua- tion <ref type="bibr">[HHN85]</ref> as already mentioned. Furthermore, external- ization of information is beneficial. Norman argues that per- ceptual processing of external information is more efficient than processing internally represented information. Combin- ing these two issues, interactive external representations can be handled with ease largely on a perceptual and physical manipulation level <ref type="bibr">[Nor93]</ref>. Only recently, a small amount of studies has focused on the value of interactivity. A study on an interactive learning environment with varying degrees of interactivity shows that there is a greater preference for the interactive version <ref type="bibr">[Ric06]</ref>. However, the study does not indicate that better learning had been achieved when interac- tivity was involved. In an insight-based study users preferred inferior visualizations with interaction over superior visual- izations without interaction <ref type="bibr">[SNLD06]</ref>.</p><p>After investigating interactivity, cognitive theories and mod- els will be assessed along their descriptive, evaluative, and generative abilities for interaction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Cognitive Theories &amp; Models</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Interactivity-as-Process</head><p>Not the features of a tool or medium are the concern of interactivity-as-process, but the process of active discourse A central idea of cognitive science that emerged in the mid 1950s is that " <ref type="bibr">[t]</ref>hinking can best be understood in terms of representational structures in the mind and computational procedures that operate on these structures." <ref type="bibr">[Tha96]</ref>. Dif- ferent approaches towards cognitive science were developed over the years: formal logic (inferences are made based on statements); rules (IF-THEN statements); concepts (frame W. Aigner / Understanding the Role and Value of Interaction: Computer science and especially HCI draw upon cog- nitive science approaches to model the interaction be- tween humans and computers in so-called cognitive ar- chitectures <ref type="bibr">[Byr03]</ref>. Examples are Model Human Proces  <ref type="bibr">[CNM83]</ref> provides a framework resulting from a synthesis of the lit- erature on cognitive psychology and human performance up to that time. It describes a system that is composed of dif- ferent types of memories and processors along with perfor- mance measures that are grounded on empirical studies. In MHP, the human mind is a specific type of an information processing unit, which has three subsystems: the sensory in- put subsystem, the central information processing subsys- tem, and the motor output subsystem. GOMS (Goals, Opera- tions, Methods, and Selection rules) <ref type="bibr">[CNM83]</ref> is an attempt to provide a framework for task analysis, which describes routine cognitive skills in terms of the four components - goals, operations, methods, and selection rules. It describes the hierarchical procedural knowledge a person must have to successfully complete a task.</p><p>Distributed Cognition largely originated from the work of Hutchins and colleagues <ref type="bibr">[Hut96]</ref>. "Cognition is said to be "distributed", meaning that it occurs not just in indi- vidual minds but through the cooperation of many individ- uals" <ref type="bibr">[Tha96]</ref>. People, tools, systems, etc. are all "media" and part of a system of nodes while human and nonhuman nodes are of the same type. Structures inside the human body as well as outside of it are part of the same cognitive sys- tem and treated equally. This means that knowledge is not only represented in the brains of individuals but also in the artifacts we are utilizing. Distributed Cognition also deals with the question of what transformations these structures undergo. In contrast to the Situated Action approach, Dis- tributed Cognition emphasizes not the individual level but the cognitive system as a whole. A central tenet of Situated Action as well as Distributed Cognition is embodiment and embodied interaction. Dourish describes it as "the creation, manipulation, and sharing of meaning through engaged in- teraction with artifacts" <ref type="bibr">[Dou01]</ref>. Another major element of Distributed Cognition is to understand the coordination among individuals and artifacts, that is, to understand how individual agents align and share within a distributed pro- cess. Thus, it is of particular interest when dealing with in- teractivity. This led to a first attempt to adopt Distributed Cognition as the underlying theory for interactive visualiza- tion in <ref type="bibr">[LNS08]</ref>.</p><p>The main points of criticism of the mentioned approaches are that neither physical nor social environments are recog- nized properly as cognitive science focuses on phenomena inside the head of a single human being. Therefore, so-called "postcognitivist theories" were developed that take these ex- ternal factors into account.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Postcognitivist Theories</head><p>Artifacts are of special interest because computer tools can be seen as cognitive artifacts for external cognition that ex- pand human capabilities <ref type="bibr">[Nor93]</ref>. Their use not only affects the individual but also social interactions. The role of ar- tifacts and social environments is emphasized in the theo- ries like Situated Action, Distributed Cognition, and Activ- ity Theory. Suchman <ref type="bibr">[Suc87]</ref> challenged the assumption that human cognition can be modeled in a computer program and introduced a new theory of Situated Action. Here, human be- ings are seen as thinking through interaction with the world rather than by means of representing it and processing these representations internally -the individual's actions are influ- enced by the context of their specific situation. It builds upon the concept that the specific situation is the most important factor in determining what people will do.</p><p>Activity Theory distinguishes clearly between individual human beings and things. Moreover, a cornerstone of Ac- tivity Theory is that people deliberately commit certain acts by using certain technologies. This is at odds with the Dis- tributed Cognition theory where both, people and artifacts are types of "media" in a system of nodes. However, Dis- tributed Cognition takes both points of view throughout the work of <ref type="bibr">[Hut96]</ref> -that of tool mediation and human perfor- mance which clearly separates humans and tools, as well as that of a cognitive system of like nodes. Activity Theory is an answer to both points of criticism of traditional cogni- tive science by including a rich social matrix of people and artifacts that grounds analysis. The unit of analysis in Ac- tivity Theory is an activity which is composed of subject, object, actions, and operations. The subject is a person or a group that is engaged in an activity. The object is the objec- tive held by the subject. Actions are goal-oriented processes that must be carried out in order to fulfill the objective and actions might have operational aspects, which are low-level processes we are not aware of most of the time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Summary &amp; Discussion</head><p>A number of traditional cognitive science approaches as well as postcognitivist theories and models were presented in the last section. Activity Theory appears to be the most encom- passing theory but also the most complex one. In terms of interactivity, traditional cognitive science focuses on user- system interaction and interaction itself is modeled mostly W. Aigner / Understanding the Role and Value of Interaction: First Steps as simple input and output channels. Postcognitivist theories go beyond interaction between people and technology and account for the objects in the world with which subjects are interacting via technology in a social context. <ref type="bibr">[GRF08]</ref>  The goal of this paper was to shed light on the concept of interactivity in the context of VA. Therefore, the central as- pect of interactivity was tackled first from the point of view of research about interactivity itself and second, by inves- tigating different cognitive theories. However, interactivity is not explicitly accounted for or modeled in these theo- ries. Following the very definition of VA as "the science of analytical reasoning facilitated by interactive visual in- terfaces" <ref type="bibr">[TC05]</ref> we can discern a focus on the aspect of interactivity-as-process in the first part of the definition. But the second part also hints towards the question of how the analytical reasoning can be supported via interaction con- cretely (interactivity-as-product). Putting it together, both perspectives, reflecting a top-down as well as a bottom-up view, are of particular importance and should be pursued in parallel. Another major aspect in VA is the intertwinedness of visual and automated analysis techniques that need to be integrated seamlessly. Special considerations are necessary to account for this also with regard to interaction. Apart from this, it is also important to take on a user's point of view and investigate how analysts see the role and value of in- teractivity. In a preliminary qualitative study we interviewed professionals in the business intelligence community. Sur- prisingly, we found that interactivity in visual methods is relatively unknown among users. However, interactivity is associated with supporting a deeper understanding of data for making well-informed decisions. Next, we plan the fol- lowing concrete next steps: to investigate Activity Theory in cooperation with cognitive science specialists in depth for grounding interactivity from a theoretical point of view and to conduct empirical studies on how interactive features are used in which contexts and for which tasks as well as to in- vestigate the effects of different degrees of interactivity. <ref type="bibr">[Kee10]</ref> KEEFE D.: Integrating Visualization and Interaction Re- search to Improve Scientific Workflows. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head>GREEN T ., RIBARSKY W., FISHER B.: Visual Analyt- ics for Complex Concepts Using a Human Cognition Model.</head><label>GREEN T</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>In 
Proc. IEEE VAST (2008), pp. 91-98. 1 
[HHN85] HUTCHINS E. L., HOLLAN J. D., NORMAN D. A.: 
Direct Manipulation Interfaces. Human-Computer Interaction 1, 
4 (1985), 311-338. 2 

5. Conclusion 

[Hut96] HUTCHINS E.: Cognition in the Wild. The MIT Press, 
Cambridge, 1996. 3 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Acting with Technology: Activity Theory and Interaction Design</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Nardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cambridge</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note>The MIT Press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A Framework of Interaction Costs in Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1149" />
			<publisher>IEEE TVCG 14</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Distributed Cognition as a Theoretical Framework for Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Nersessian</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Stasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1173" />
			<publisher>IEEE TVCG 14</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mental Models, Visual Reasoning and Interaction in Information Visualization: A Top-down Perspective</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Stasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<publisher>IEEE TVCG 16</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1008" to="1010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Psychology of Everyday Things. Basic Books</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
			<pubPlace>1, 2</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Things That Make Us Smart: Defending Human Attributes In The Age Of The Machine. Basic Books</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Norman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Pike</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">,</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Connell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The Science of Interaction. Information Visualization 8</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="274" to="275" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Is Interactivity Actually Important? In Proc. Australasian Conf. on Interactive Entertainment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Richards</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="68" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Guest Editors&apos; Introduction: Interacting with Digital Tabletops</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Scott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Carpendale</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<publisher>IEEE CGA 26</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">An Insight-Based Longitudinal Study of Visual Analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>North</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Duca</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1522" />
			<publisher>IEEE TVCG 12</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">SPENCE R.: Information Visualization: Design for Interaction</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>, 2 ed. Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle River, NJ</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defining Virtual Reality: Dimensions Determining Telepresence</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">73-93. 2</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>STEUER J</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
				<idno>Austria (No. 820928). [Str04] STROMER-GALLEY J.: Interactivity-as-Product and Interactivity-as-Process. The Information Society 20</idno>
		<title level="m">and the Federal Ministry of Transport, Innovation and Technology</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="394" to="396" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Plans and Situated Actions: The Problem of Human-Machine Communication</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1987" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Cambridge University Press, Cambridge</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Cognitive Architecture. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Byrne</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="120" />
			<pubPlace>Hillsdale, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Illuminating the Path: The Research and Development Agenda for Visual Analytics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Thomas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>IEEE Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Psychology of Human-Computer Interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Card</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Newell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Moran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983" />
			<publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Hillsdale, NJ</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Mind: Introduction to Cognitive Science</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Cambridge</note>
	<note>The MIT Press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Where the Action Is: The Foundations of Embodied Interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
<note type="report_type">Cambridge</note>
	<note>The MIT Press</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Information Visualization: Perception for Design, 2nd edition ed</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Ware</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<pubPlace>Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Interactive Technologies</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Capturing Reasoning Process Through User Interaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Ribarsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">In Proc. IEEE EuroVAST</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Toward a Deeper Understanding of the Role of Interaction in Information Visualization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Yi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Stasko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Jacko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
			<publisher>IEEE TVCG 13</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1231" to="1232" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
