<Publication>
  <id>TUW-213513</id>
  <title></title>
  <abstractText>Software models, traditionally used mainly for documentation and informal specification purposes, are becoming first-class development artifacts in the area of Model-driven Engineering (MDE). In MDE, code is generated automatically from multi-view models described in languages like the Unified Modeling Language (UML) 1. Maintaining consistency between the different views of a model is crucial for the generation of correct code. As software models undergo evolution, particularly in cooperative development environments, tool support for evolution tasks like versioning and merging is indispensable. It is important to thoroughly test such tools in order to avoid the introduction of inconsistent models. However, real-life test cases that cover sufficient evolution scenarios are difficult to obtain. We therefore suggest a method to generate artificial scenarios to facilitate fuzz testing of model evolution tools. In previous work [2] we presented an approach to merge concurrently evolved sequence diagrams with respect to the behavior modeled in their corresponding state machines view. We described the sequence diagram merging (SDM) problem formally, suggested a method to solve this problem, and implemented a prototype based on the EMF framework 2. As there were no benchmarks available, we manually created a set of test cases. However, this is a very cumbersome testing method particularly when a good coverage is needed. A set of randomly generated instances solves this problem, as we show in the following.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology</institution>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Grammar-based Fuzzing of Model Evolution Scenarios</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Conclusion and Future Work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>