<Publication>
  <id>TUW-198401</id>
  <title></title>
  <abstractText>incidents pose a major threat to the efficient execution of corporate strategies and business processes. Although companies generally spend a lot of money on security companies are often not aware of their spending on security and even more important if these investments into security are effective. This paper provides decision makers with an overview of decision support techniques, describes pros and cons of these methodologies. 1 INTRODUCTION Companies are often not aware of their spending on security and even more important if the investments into security are effective. The definition of security safeguards is often a result of current needs or influenced by security problems that may go public. When seeking to select the most appropriate set of measures and, thus, the right level of security investments, decision makers are challenged by (i) having to concentrate resources on value-generating and supplementary business processes while (ii) having to consider multiple strategic objectives that are often conflicting as well as (iii) the cost-efficient usage of the available resources and interdependencies between the systems and (iv) a variety of potential technologies and potential systems. As a consequence security decisions provide only punctual solutions and are made without considering the costs and benefits of introducing theses measures. Accordingly, a variety of approaches have been introduced that aim to support decision makers in identifying the &quot;right&quot; investment candidates. This paper provides decision makers with an overview of common methods for the evaluation and selection of security safeguards and describes pros and cons of these methodologies. One major focus of this evaluation lies on identifying the method&apos;s capabilities in (i) considering business processes for aligning expenditure to actual business needs and (ii) inte</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>A COMPARISON OF SECURITY SAFEGUARD SELECTION METHODS Thomas Neubauer Secure Business Austria</string>
    <string>Favoritenstrasse 16</string>
    <string>1040 Vienna</string>
    <string>Austria neubauer@securityresearchacat Keywords: Security</string>
    <string>Risk Management</string>
    <string>Economics</string>
    <string>Decision Support Abstract: IT security</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>COMPARISON</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>