<Publication>
  <id>TUW-201167</id>
  <title>Using a Solution Archive to Enhance Metaheuristics for the Rooted Delay-Constrained Minimum Spanning Tree Problem</title>
  <note>Mario Ruthmair, Andreas Hubmer, and Günther R. Raidl Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</note>
  <abstractText>When designing a communication network with a central server broadcasting information to all the participants of the network, some applications, such as video conferences, require a limitation of the maximal delay from the server to each client. Beside this delay-constraint minimizing the cost of establishing the network is in most cases an important design criterion. This network design problem can be modeled as an N P-hard combinatorial optimization problem called rooted delay-constrained minimum spanning tree (RDCMST) problem. The objective is to find a minimum cost spanning tree of a given graph with the additional constraint that the sum of delays along the paths from a specified root node to any other node must not exceed a given delay-bound. More formally, we are given an undirected graph G = (V, E) with a set V of n nodes, a set E of m edges, a cost function c : E → R</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology</institution>
          <country>Vienna</country>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>+ 0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>The Solution Archive</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Integration in Metaheuristics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>