<Publication>
  <id>TUW-228620</id>
  <title></title>
  <note>PREFACE Security and privacy in business networking Sven Wohlgemuth &amp; Stefan Sackmann &amp; Noboru Sonehara &amp; A Min Tjoa # Institute of Information Management, University of St. Gallen 2014</note>
  <doi>10.1007/s12525-014-0158-6</doi>
  <abstractText>Business networking relies on application-specific quantity and quality of information in order to support social infrastructures in, e.g., energy allocation coordinated by smart grids, healthcare services with electronic health records, traffic management with personal sensors, RFID in retail and logistics , or integration of individuals&apos; social network information into good, services, and rescue operations. Due to the increasing reliance of networking applications on sharing ICT services , dependencies threaten privacy, security, and reliability of information and, thus, innovative business applications in smart societies. Resilience is becoming a new security approach , since it takes dependencies into account and aims at achieving equilibriums in case of opposite requirements. This special issue on &apos;Security and Privacy in Business Networking&apos; contributes to the journal &apos;Electronic Markets&apos; by introducing a different view on achieving acceptable secure business networking applications in spite of threats due to covert channels. This view is on adapting resilience to enforcement of IT security in business networking applications. Our analysis shows that privacy is an evidence to measure and improve trustworthy relationships and reliable interactions between participants of business processes and their IT systems. The articles of this special issue, which have been accepted after a double-blind peer review, contribute to this view on interdis-ciplinary security engineering in regard to the stages of security and privacy requirements analysis, enforcement of resulting security requirements for an information exchange, testing with a privacy-preserving detection of policy violations , and knowledge management for the purpose of keeping business processes resilient. His Cabinet 2013). One aim of these initiatives is that systems, such as business networking applications, social infrastructures, and a society become resilient. Changes and vulnerabilities should be identified and analyzed to foresee and prevent incidents of any kind, as well as to react accordingly in acceptable time. Resilient ICT then supports the increased, sustainable welfare of a society. The key approach for gaining information on vulnerabil-ities and predicting incidents will be the ability to access and to analyze huge amounts of data in nearly real-time and to implement so-called Big Data analytics successfully. Service providers will collect, aggregate, and analyze data from various sources provided by</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Business networking Resilience Information exchange Security Privacy Enforcement Business networking and resilience At present</string>
    <string>one of the most promising visions for business networking is the exploitation of information with information and communication technology (ICT)</string>
    <string>in particular by Big Data analytics with cyber-physical systems (CPS) (acatech 2011; Wahlster and Müller 2013) IBM calls it &apos;Smarter Planet&apos; (IBM Corporation 2008)</string>
    <string>the European Commission (2010) has started the corresponding program &apos;Horizon 2020-A Digital Agenda for Europe&apos;</string>
    <string>and Japan proposes the &apos;Declaration to be the World&apos;s Most Advanced IT Nation&apos; (Prime Minister of Japan and CPS</string>
    <string>eg</string>
    <string>business networks</string>
    <string>social S Wohlgemuth (*) CASED</string>
    <string>System Security Lab</string>
    <string>Mornewegstr 32</string>
    <string>64293 Darmstadt</string>
    <string>Germany e-mail: svenwohlgemuth@trustcasedde S Sackmann Martin Luther University Halle Wittenberg</string>
    <string>Universitätsring 3</string>
    <string>06108 Halle/Saale</string>
    <string>Germany N Sonehara National Institute of Informatics</string>
    <string>Information and Society Research Division</string>
    <string>2-1-2 Hitotsubashi</string>
    <string>Chiyoda-ku</string>
    <string>Tokyo 101-8430</string>
    <string>Japan A Tjoa Vienna University of Technology</string>
    <string>Institute for Software Technology</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Electron Markets</institution>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>PET and dependencies</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Papers within ICT Resilience</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>