<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Justyna Patalas-Maliszewska Dr., University of Zielona Góra, Poland/</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The author&apos;s software system for planning and selection of personnel in SME Abstract: The strategic management of intellectual capital involves rethinking how the companies creates value from a knowledge -centric perspective and redesigning and orchestrating the role of staff knowledge in the firm&apos;s strategy. This paper presents the author&apos;s software system for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge. This software is a computer implementation of the method for planning and selection of personnel in SME. information systems that support knowledge management in SMEs can give guarantees a constant competitive advantage in the market. Keywords: intellectual capital, strategic knowledge management 1. Introduction The advantage of a company in the SME sector (small and medium sizes enterprises) is determined by effectiveness and the extent of the knowledge-workers&apos; involvement. The role of intellectual capital management consists in striving to increase the share of immaterial resources (at the costs of the material ones) in the generated products, services, and the total market value of an organization (Król and Ludwiczyński, 2007). The article presents the description of strategic knowledge resources in companies and author&apos;s method for plannig and selection of personnel in SME (see chapter 2). In the third chapter the author&apos;s software system for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge is presented on example of the decision-making situation in which an innovative SME is considering the employment of a new m-th employee. The summary shows the</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Database of the values of the characteristics of innovation: xi in SME for k-companies i,k∈N</p><p>The decision-making model for the assessment of the efficiency of the selection of the m-th employee for an SME: • Built on the basis of a defined database with the use of GMDH,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Combined selected indicators.</p><p>Is an employee being sought who guarantees that the SME may gain the A four-element method for the planning and selection of strategic knowledge resources in SME has been built. The four elements are:</p><p>• A reference model of an SME-sector company, • The value of the personnel usefulness function desired values of the qualification criteria for an innovative company? The implementation of data which is characteristic for an SME-sector for each m-th employee in SME • The qualifying criteria in an innovative company, • An algorithm which will enable the connection of company in a computer program (consistent with the reference model)</p><p>the value of strategic resources of knowledge to the value of the qualifying criteria for an innova- tive company -GMDH.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 2:</head><p>The application of a defined decision-making model with use of the imple- mented data of a company with the aid of a computer program The method was created on the basis of methods for the assessment of capital value and on the characteristics of innovative companies. It combines available knowl- edge gained from literature, and experiences of SMEs which have the potential for innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 3:</head><p>The forecasting of the value of strategic knowledge resources in an innova- tive SME (the value of personnel usefulness function); depending on the defined values of the innovation characteristics The method allows for making an assessment of the future value of the decision about the selection of an em- ployee in the relation to increasing innovation in a SME- sector company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 4:</head><p>Conducting an interview with a potential employee using the program -  <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> The decision-making situation in which an innovative SME is considering the employment of a new m-th employee The decision-making situation of the SME sector has been presented; this decides on the employment of new employees in sales. Also the author has described the example of the company A2, which is looking for an em- ployee to the fill the position of 'regional assistant'. The company expects to retain its current level of innovation. <ref type="figure">Fig. 5</ref> Example of using the author's software system Using the proposed system, it is possible to check to see whether the company complies with the specified refer- ence model. A potential new employee selects actions that will be performed in the company. The developed reference model will help companies to determine the work place for a new employee.</p><p>Through the use of the tool known as the system to sup- port decision making at the strategic level with regards to the assessment of knowledge in an innovative SME, which is the implementation of the method for planning and selection of personnel in SME, the following informa- tion was produced: • For m4 -Regional Assistant: <ref type="figure">*   =-0,6490+3,4592X7-2,2539X13- 2,0984X7  2 1,7486X13  2 +3,8323X7X13, where</ref> X7 -number of employees with scientific degrees, X13 -the number of purchased and used licenses. <ref type="figure">Fig. 3</ref> Example of using the author's software system Stage 3: For the new potential employee as a 'Regional Assistant', by using the decision model we obtain the following fore- cast of the personnel usefulness function, the company's request for the sample of A2's values of characteristics of innovation <ref type="figure">:  m4   *   =-0,6490+3,4592X7-2,2539X13-2,0984X7  2 -  1,7486X13  2 +3,8323X7X13, where</ref> X7 -number of employees with scientific degrees, X13 -the number of purchased and used licenses Using the the author's software system, the actual value of the personnel usefulness function for a new employee is checked (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 6):</ref> thodical and uniformity, fairness and impartiality, profes- sionalism. <ref type="figure">References   Fig. 6</ref> Example of using the author's software system Then we compare the actual value of the personnel use- fulness function with the expected new employee. If these values are similar, it is assumed that the employment of the employee will allow us to maintain the current level of innovation within the company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>m4</head><p>The actual value of the function: <ref type="table">Wm4 = 19</ref> The forecast value of the function <ref type="figure">:   Wm4   *   =-0,6490+3,4592X7-2,2539X13+2,0984X7  2 -  1,7486X13  2 +3,8323X7X13 = 19,6231</ref> for X7 -number of employees with scientific degrees -X7 = 2, The company can decide to recruit new employees for the position of 'Regional assistant' because the predicted value of the personnel usefulness function for the new employee is in line with the actual value of the function, which would allow the company to maintain a certain level of innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion and direction for further</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>work</head><p>This paper presents the author's system for supporting decision making at the strategic level with regards to the assessment of knowledge in an innovative SME. Through the example of using this system, the author shows how the forecasting of the values of strategic knowledge re- sources (values of the personnel usefulness function for the m-th employee) will be carried out. The current state of advancement of research allows the application of this system for SME sector in line adopted reference model (the reference model of SME is strictly defined in the other works of the author). The selection of employees using the proposed system is characterized by objectivity, me- 1. Król H., Ludwiczyński A. Human Resource Man- agement, PWN, Warszawa (in polish)., 2007. 2. Barthelme F., Ermine J. L, Rosenthal-Sabroux C.</p><p>An architecture for knowledge evolution in orga- nisations. European Journal of Operational Re- search, 1998. 3. Basu A.. Perspectives on operations research in data and knowledge management. European Journal of Operational Research, 1998. 4. Carayannis E. G. The strategic management of technological learning in project/program man- agement: the role of extranets, intranets and in- telligent agents in knowledge generation, diffu- sion, and leveraging. Technovation. Vol. 18, No. 11. Elsevier. 1998. pp. 697-703. 5. Drew S. Building knowledge management into strategy. Making sense of a new perspective. Long Range Plan.1999. 6. Chen YM, Liang MW. Design and implementa- tion of a collaborative engineering information system for allied concurrent engineering. Int J Comput Integrated Manuf. 1999. 7. Senn J.A. Information Systems in Management.</p><p>Wadsworth CA. 1990. 8. Chrisman J. J., Chua, J. H., Zahra, S. A. Creat- ing wealth in family firms through managing re- sources: Comments and extensions. Entrepre- neurship  <ref type="figure">Tytuł: Autorski system informatyczny wspomagający  podejmowanie decyzji w zakresie planowania i dobo- ru personelu w MSP  Streszczenie:</ref> Strategiczne zarządzanie kapitałem inte- lektualnym w przedsiębiorstwach, w szczególności w sektorze MSP, wymaga właściwego postrzegania warto- ści wiedzy oraz pracowników wiedzy. W artykule przed- stawiono autorski system informatyczny wspomagający podejmowanie decyzji w zakresie planowania i doboru personelu w MSP. System ten stanowi implementację autorskiej metody planowania i doboru personelu w MSP. Dr nauk ekonomicznych, trener REFA, Akredytowany Konsultant Funduszy Europejskich z 8 letnim doświadczeniem. Specjalizuje się w:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>zarządzaniu</head><p>strategicznym oraz opracowywaniu strategii rozwoju dla przedsiębiorstw, zarządzaniu wiedzą, zarządzaniu projektami. Stypendyst- ka międzynarodowych stypendiów naukowych (m.in. w ramach 7 PR UE, MNiSW). Ma na swoim koncie liczne prace i publikacje. Prowadzi wykłady i zajęcia na uczelniach wyższych w Polsce i za granicą (Uniwersytet Zielonogórski, BTU Cottbus, Uniwersytet Techniczny w Wiedniu, Austria).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>e-mail: j.patalas@iizp.uz.zgora.pl</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>X13</head><label></label><figDesc>-the number of purchased and used licenses -X13 = 1</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Application of</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Resource: 

Resources: 

collective 
knowledge 
and 

critical resources in a company 

capabilities that reside in the 

represented by the knowledge, 

organization 
[Hamel 
and 

skills and capabilities of individu-

Prahalad, 1994]. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head>facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge, which considers all elements of the presented method. Strategic Knowledge Resource: personnel SME usefulness function Wnm for the m-th employee in the SME:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The next chapter presents the author's software sys-
tem for </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>Stage 1 :</head><label>Stage 1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>Stage 5 :</head><label>Stage 5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>The comparison of the forecasted value of a strategic resource of knowl-

edge with its current value 

Stage 6: 

The recommendation of the m-th employee (in terms of the smallest 

discrepancy between the forecasted value of a strategic resource of 

knowledge with its current value) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>Stage 2 :</head><label>Stage 2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table>Stage 1: 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>Stage 4 :</head><label>Stage 4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false"><head>Stage 5 :</head><label>Stage 5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
