<Publication>
  <id>TUW-233317</id>
  <title>QualityTrails: Data Quality Provenance as a Basis for Sensemaking</title>
  <note>Christian Bors 1 , Theresia Gschwandtner 1 , Silvia Miksch 1 , and Johannes G ¨ artner 2 1 Institute of Software Technology &amp; Interactive Systems (ISIS), Vienna University of Technology, Austria, {surname}@ifs.tuwien.ac.at 2 XIMES GmbH, Vienna, Austria, gaertner@ximes.com</note>
  <abstractText>Visual Analytics prototypes increasingly support human sensemak-ing through providing Provenance information. For data analysts the challenge of knowledge generation starts with assessing the quality of a data set, but Provenance is not yet utilized to aid this task. This position paper aims at characterizing the complexity of Visual Analytics methods introducing Provenance in Data Quality by highlighting the challenges of (In Data Quality (DQ) assessment one of the central questions is, &apos;Is the Data Quality good enough for analysis to produce meaningful results?&apos; The quality of data analysis is highly dependent on the quality of the underlying data. Thus, a prerequisite of any data analysis, such as creating visualizations and performing analytical reasoning, is assessing and improving DQ. Data cleansing is an iterative task that requires user expertise and domain knowledge of the data provided [7]. DQ control can be understood as a combination of data quality assessment, the data cleansing process, as well as applying transformations to change a data set&apos;s structure. Kandel et al. [7] argue that integrating interactive and visual systems could facilitate these tasks as well as data verification. Yet, the analyst is left with the decision about when quality is sufficient to start analysis, or if the data is worth further manipulating at all. Sensemaking is an integral part of Visual Analytics (VA). During DQ assessment the analyst needs to take into account not only the actual data, but also implicit information, like how the data was created or its transformation history. A data set already might have been analyzed by someone else, generating a transformation</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>1) generating Provenance from Data Quality Control and (2) sensemaking based on Data Quality Provenance Keywords: data provenance</string>
    <string>analytic provenance</string>
    <string>sensemaking</string>
    <string>data quality</string>
    <string>quality metrics</string>
    <string>visual data analysis Index Terms: Human-centered Computing [Visualization]: Vi-sualization application domains-Visual Analytics Mathematics of computing [Probability and statistics]: Statistical paradigms-Exploratory data analysis 1 INTRODUCTION</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>CHALLENGES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>Provenance from Data Quality Control</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>OUTLOOK</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Sensemaking based on Data Quality Provenance</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>