<Publication>
  <id>TUW-140229</id>
  <title>An Approach for Detecting Learning Styles in Learning Management</title>
  <abstractText>Detecting the needs of learners is a challenging but essential task to be able to provide adaptivity. In this paper we present a tool that enables learning management systems (LMS) to detect learning styles based on the behavior of learners during an online course. By calculating the learning styles and filling the student model of LMS with such personal data, a basis for adaptivity is provided. MASPLANG [2] and CS383 [3]. But these systems use a questionnaire for detecting learning styles. Garcia et al. [4] investigated the use of Bayesian networks to detect learning styles based on the behavior of learners in a web-based educational system. While their work is focused on the use of Bayesian networks, our approach sums up indications of preferences based on patterns, equally to the approach of learning style questionnaires. Moreover, we propose a tool for LMS in general rather than for one specific system.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Systems* Sabine Graf Vienna University of Technology Women&apos;s Postgraduate College for Internet Technologies</string>
    <string>Vienna</string>
    <string>Austria graf@wittuwienacat Kinshuk Massey University Department of Information Systems Palmerston North</string>
    <string>New Zealand kinshuk@ieeeorg</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>1.</level>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>* 2. Patterns of behavior</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>Tool architecture</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Figure 1. Tool architecture</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Data extraction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>Calculation of learning styles</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.</level>
      <title>Conclusion and future work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>