<Publication>
  <id>TUW-192724</id>
  <title>A model of employee selection for SME based on</title>
  <note>Community&apos;s, Seventh Framework Programme [FP7/2007-2013; FP7-PEOPLE-IEF-2008], under grant agreement n°[ 235585] &quot;SKnowInnov&quot;.</note>
  <abstractText>Human resource strategy can emerge within a decentralized decision structure that gives managers autonomy to take responsive actions while overall strategic direction is considered within a strategic planning process. This study defines the concept of employee selection (especially strategic employee selection) and hypothesizes on the positive correlation between innovation characteristic in SME and value of strategic employee (the so called personnel usefulness function). An empirical study illustrates the importance of both elements in an integrative human resource strategy formation process particularly for firms operating in the international environments. Keywords: the personnel usefulness function, innovation characteristics, the employee selection efficiency method. 1. Introduction Growing international competition necessitates increasing interest in new scientific advancements and new solutions in the field of management based on innovation transfer. Management staff forms a basis for expediting structural changes in the regional economy. Staff is also a decisive factor for enhancing competitiveness. In the knowledge based economy, while trying to maintain their position in the market or access new markets, managers and employees need to improve their skills. This will help in being able to use innovative technologies that exist all over the world. It is generally recognized that effective human resource strategy formation processes consist of central planning activities orchestrated at the corporate strategic apex as well as emerging strategic decisions influenced by empowered managers within the organization [Hill and Jones, 2000; Johnson and Scholes, 2002; Mintzberg et al., 2003]. 1 Acknowledgement: The research leading to these results has received funding from the European Companies operating in a market economy need to introduce changes to their systems organisation and management. In business practice, decision making in a company depends on activity, competition, changing external factors, e.g. technical advancement, and results achieved by research and development departments, knowledge, employees&apos; skills, social relations, know-how, and in particular, effective investment in intellectual are an added value for a company. Companies investing in human capital and work systems acquire competitive advantage thanks to their readiness to learn and adopt new qualifications as well as efficient communication and information channels. Small and medium sizes enterprises (SMEs) that are about to make decision concerning the employee selection tend to make a pre-evaluation of the efficiency of this decision. There is a demand for developing the method that would diminish the risk of an inadequate employee selection and at the same time would allow to solve the problems which otherwise could be missed. A relevant framework to this issue is based on a database referring to: The SME, with defined the selected functional area, the business processes, the workplaces and the personnel usefulness function for m-the employee in the n-th SME: W nm , n,m∈N is given. Allowing responding to the following question: Whether a existed (given) the employee selection efficiency method based on the innovation transfer in the small and medium enterprises (SME)? It can be concluded that there is a need to define the criteria of the employee selection (especially strategic employee) efficiency in the SME. Consequently an appropriate reference model of the company should be developed to enable both defining: the needs in the areas of functionality and the success evaluation of employee selection. Such a model should provide a kind of guideline for the future employee selection framework. The decision as far as the selection of the proper employee should be preceded by the management profitability assessment and the prospect advantage. In order to view the prediction of the described innovation indicators the authorized consulting system supporting decision making enabling to asses and forecast of knowledge in SMEs (software) can be used (an Advisory Computer System for Forecasting the Efficiency of a Strategic Employee Selection in Small and Medium Enterprises). This tool is the implementation of the method of assessment of efficiency strategic employee selection based on innovation indicators in the small and medium enterprises (SME), which in this paper is presented. This computer program could be a supplement as the module to the for example compute system: Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP). ERP is process oriented software that implementation can improve business processes running through functional areas of a company onto computer system [Klaus at al., 2000]. Implementation of ERP is a strategic decision, that results about efficiency of business processes, charge of resources and generally about compete and management efficiency of the enterprise for the next years.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>innovation transfer Justyna Patalas-Maliszewska 1; 1</string>
    <string>Irene Krebs 2 1 University of Vienna/Austria</string>
    <string>University of Zielona Góra</string>
    <string>Polen</string>
    <string>jpatalas@iizpuzzgorapl 2 Brandenburg University of Technology Cottbus</string>
    <string>Germany</string>
    <string>krebs@iittu-cottbusde</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2.</level>
      <title>The employee selection efficiency method -ESE</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>4</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>A model of employee selection for SME</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.</level>
      <title>A polynomial decision-making model using GMDH algorithm</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>2</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>m</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>0,06</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>10</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>2000</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>7</level>
      <title>12</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>Concluding remarks</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>