<Publication>
  <id>TUW-221215</id>
  <title></title>
  <note>Hiermit erkläre ich, dass ich diese Arbeit selbständig verfasst habe, dass ich die verwendeten Quellen und Hilfsmittel vollständig angegeben habe und dass ich die Stellen der Arbeit -einschließlich Tabellen, Karten und Abbildungen -, die anderen Werken oder dem Internet im Wortlaut oder dem Sinn nach entnommen sind, auf jeden Fall unter Angabe der Quelle als Entlehnung kenntlich gemacht habe. ______________________ ______________________________________________ (Ort, Datum) (Unterschrift Verfasser)</note>
  <abstractText>Danksagung Ich möchte mich vor allem bei Günther Raidl für die Möglichkeit bedanken, meine Diplomarbeit an seiner Abteilung zu verfassen, und bei Bin Hu für die ausgezeichnete Betreuung. Weiters möchte ich mich bei meinen Eltern bedanken, die mir das Studium finanziell ermöglicht haben. Zudem habe ich ihnen auch zu verdanken, dass sie mein Interesse an Computern frühzeitig erkannt und gefördert haben. Abstract The Selective Graph Coloring Problem (SGCP) is about finding a subgraph of a particular structure whose chromatic number is as low as possible. The original graph is divided into several clusters, and from each cluster the subgraph has to contain exactly one node. This problem is NP-hard and therefore it is usually solved by means of heuristics. I implemented several variants of an algorithm making use of Variable Neighborhood Search (VNS) to search the space of solution candidates and then evaluating the solution using heuristic or exact methods. Furthermore, each variant can be used with or without a solution archive, i.e. a data structure in which previously found solutions are stored so that duplicates need not be re-evaluated but can be efficiently converted into new solutions instead. For exact computation of the chromatic number integer linear programming was used. To obtain an upper bound a variant of greedy coloring was used. Another variant of the algorithm also counts the number of conflicts that would appear if one color less were used. Finally, two methods were implemented to obtain a lower bound: maximum clique and linear programming using column generation. The program was tested with various instances from the literature. My algorithm often finished computation within a very short time, but in general it led to slightly worse results. Kurzfassung Beim Selective Graph Coloring Problem (SGCP) geht es darum, einen Teilgraphen mit spezieller Struktur zu finden, dessen chromatische Zahl so niedrig wie möglich ist. Der Ursprungsgraph ist in mehrere Cluster unterteilt, und von jedem Cluster muss der Teilgraph genau einen Knoten enthalten. Dieses Problem ist NP-schwer und wird daher meistens mit Heuristiken gelöst. Ich habe mehrere Varianten eines Algorithmus implementiert, der Variable Neighborhood Search (VNS) benutzt, um den Lösungsraum zu durchsuchen, und dann die gefundene Lösung mit heuristischen oder exakten Methoden evaluiert. Jede Variante kann mit oder ohne ein Lösungsarchiv verwendet werden. Ein Lösungsarchiv ist eine Datenstruktur, in der bereits gefundene Lösungen gespeichert werden, so dass Duplikate nicht neu evaluiert werden müssen, sondern effizient zu neuen Lösungen konvertiert werden können. Um eine obere Schranke zu errechnen, wurde eine Variante von Greedy Coloring verwendet. Eine weitere Variante des Algorithmus zählt auch die Anzahl der Konflikte, die entstünden, würde eine Farbe weniger verwendet werden. Schließlich wurden zwei Methoden umgesetzt, um eine untere Schranke zu berechnen: maximale Clique und lineare Programmierung mit Spaltengenerierung. Das Programm wurde mit verschiedenen Instanzen aus der Literatur getestet. Mein Algorithmus beendete die Berechnungen oft schon nach sehr kurzer Laufzeit, führte aber im Allgemeinen zu geringfügig schlechteren Ergebnissen. Introduction Graphs are a useful tool for modelling real-world problems, as they can serve as an abstraction for various things, such as networks and maps. For this reason, the solution of problems related to graph theory may have an impact in real life. Computer science students usually learn about some of these problems as well as algorithms for solving them in advanced courses on algorithmics. Topics commonly discussed in these courses include shortest path problems, finding the maximal flow in a network, and the Traveling Salesperson Problem. Depth First Search, Breadth First Search, Dijkstra&apos;s algorithm, the Bellman-Ford algorithm, the Floyd-Warshall algorithm, Johnson&apos;s algorithm, the Ford-Fulkerson method, preflow-push algorithms and other methods belong to the general education of any computer scientist specializing in algorithms. Graph coloring usually does not appear in these courses, but it is still an important problem about which many papers have been published. Applications of graph coloring include time tabling and various forms of allocation tasks [10]. Since it is an NP-equivalent problem, various heuristics have been proposed to get good results in a reasonable amount of time. The selective graph coloring problem is an extension of graph coloring and for this reason, it is NP-hard as well. It is about finding a subgraph consisting of one node of each cluster that has a chromatic number as low as possible. For most researchers the motivation to study this problem has been its relevance to optical networks [39]. Although some papers have been published that propose efficient solution algorithms for this problem, by far not all possible solution algorithms have been explored yet. This was my motivation for choosing this problem as the topic of my diploma thesis. In this thesis, I will present diverse variants of a heuristic solution algorithm for the selective graph coloring problem and the results obtained for some test instances. The algorithm is based on variable neighborhood search for scanning the solution space. Each solution is evaluated using exact or heuristic methods. 4 CHAPTER 1. INTRODUCTION The exact method is exact but slow. Regarding heuristics mainly an upper bound is computed, but there are also variants calculating a number of conflicts that would arise with one color less and giving a lower bound. In addition a solution archive has been implemented, which makes it possible to avoid duplicates during the search space exploration and easily find new solutions not evaluated as local optima yet. Figure 1.1 shows a graph with several clusters and a possible solution subgraph,</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Selective Graph Coloring Problem DIPLOMARBEIT zur Erlangung des akademischen Grades Diplom-Ingenieur im Rahmen des Studiums Computational Intelligence eingereicht von Claus-Dieter Volko Matrikelnummer 0102122 an der Fakultät für Informatik der Technischen Universität Wien Betreuung Betreuer/in: Univ-Prof Dipl-Ing Dr Günther Raidl Mitwirkung: Univ-Ass Dipl-Ing Dr Bin Hu Wien</string>
    <string>31032013 (Unterschrift Verfasser/in) (Unterschrift Betreuer/in) Technische Universität Wien A-1040 Wien ▪ Karlsplatz 13 ▪ Tel +43-1-58801-0 ▪ wwwtuwienacat Erklärung zur Verfassung der Arbeit Claus-Dieter Volko Hungereckstr 60/2</string>
    <string>1230 Wien</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Contents Chapter 1</institution>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>1.2.</level>
      <title>APPLICATIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.2</level>
      <title>Applications</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref31</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.3</level>
      <title>Formal Definition and Complexity</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref3</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>6</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Chapter 2 Literature Survey</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>Selective Graph Coloring Problem and</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref31</string>
        <string>ref23</string>
        <string>ref24</string>
        <string>ref17</string>
        <string>ref27</string>
        <string>ref18</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>8</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Graph Coloring</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref3</string>
        <string>ref5</string>
        <string>ref33</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2.</level>
      <title>GRAPH COLORING</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>9</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref34</string>
        <string>ref29</string>
        <string>ref19</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Chapter 3 Methods</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>12</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Metaheuristics</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref30</string>
        <string>ref20</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.</level>
      <title>METAHEURISTICS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>13</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.1</level>
      <title>Solution Representation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.2</level>
      <title>Initialization</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.3</level>
      <title>Local Search</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.</level>
      <title>METAHEURISTICS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>15</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.4</level>
      <title>Variable Neighborhood Descent</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref16</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.5</level>
      <title>Variable Neighborhood Search</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref12</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>16</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.</level>
      <title>SOLUTION EVALUATION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>17</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>Solution Evaluation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.1</level>
      <title>Upper Bound: Maximal Degree</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref1</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>18</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.2</level>
      <title>Upper Bound: Greedy Coloring</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.</level>
      <title>SOLUTION EVALUATION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>19</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.3</level>
      <title>Minimal Conflicts Heuristic</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>20</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.4</level>
      <title>Lower Bound: Maximal Clique</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref33</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.</level>
      <title>SOLUTION EVALUATION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>21</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.5</level>
      <title>Exact Method: Integer Linear Programming</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>22</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>CHAPTER 3. METHODS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.6</level>
      <title>Lower Bound: Linear Programming with Column Generation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Minimize</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Maximize</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3.</level>
      <title>SOLUTION ARCHIVE</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>23</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>Solution Archive</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref35</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.4</level>
      <title>Complete Algorithm</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>24</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Chapter 4 Testing Environment</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref31</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>28</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Chapter 5 Computational Results</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref31</string>
        <string>ref32</string>
        <string>ref27</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.1</level>
      <title>Preliminary Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>31</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Instance</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.2</level>
      <title>Discussion and Final Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Instance</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>6</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>7</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>8</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>9</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5.19</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref1</id>
      <referenceIdString>b0</referenceIdString>
      <title>On colouring the nodes of a network</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the Cambridge Philosophical Society</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Tutte</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>And</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>1941</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1941</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref2</id>
      <referenceIdString>b1</referenceIdString>
      <source>J. Brown: Chromatic scheduling and the chromatic number problem. Management Science, volume 19, issue 4, pages 456-463</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1972</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1972</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref3</id>
      <referenceIdString>b2</referenceIdString>
      <source>R. Karp: Reducibility Among Combinatorial Problems. Complexity of Computer Computations, pages 85-103</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1972</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1972</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref4</id>
      <referenceIdString>b3</referenceIdString>
      <source>Illinois Journal of Mathematics, volume 21</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>W</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <note>Haken: Every Planar Map is Four Colorable</note>
      <pageFrom>429</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>567</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>1977</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1977</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref5</id>
      <referenceIdString>b4</referenceIdString>
      <source>F. Leighton: A Graph Coloring Algorithm for Large Scheduling Problems. Journal of Research of the National Bureau of Standards, volume 84, issue 6, pages 489-506</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1979</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1979</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref6</id>
      <referenceIdString>b5</referenceIdString>
      <source>J. Peemöller: A correction to Brelaz&apos;s modification of Brown&apos;s coloring algorithm</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1983</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1983</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref7</id>
      <referenceIdString>b6</referenceIdString>
      <title>Jackowski: A generalized implicit enumeration algorithm for graph coloring</title>
      <source>Communications of the ACM</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>B</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>1985</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1985</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref8</id>
      <referenceIdString>b7</referenceIdString>
      <source>de Werra: Using Tabu Search Techniques for Graph Coloring. Computing, volume 39</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Hertz</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <pageFrom>345</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>351</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>1987</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1987</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref9</id>
      <referenceIdString>b8</referenceIdString>
      <source>C. Morgenstern: Distributed Coloration Neighborhood Search. DIMACS Series in Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science, volume 26, pages 335-357</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1996</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1996</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref10</id>
      <referenceIdString>b9</referenceIdString>
      <title>Sivarajan: Routing and wavelength assignment in alloptical networks</title>
      <source>IEEE/ACM Trans. Networking</source>
      <publisher>R. Ramaswami and K</publisher>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1995</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1995</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref11</id>
      <referenceIdString>b10</referenceIdString>
      <title>Ferland: Genetic and hybrid algorithms for graph coloring</title>
      <source>Annals of Operations Research</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>J</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>1996</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1996</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref12</id>
      <referenceIdString>b11</referenceIdString>
      <source>Hansen: Variable neighborhood search</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>P</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <note>Computers and Operations Research</note>
      <publicationDateString>1097-11</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1097</publicationYear>
      <publicationMonth>11</publicationMonth>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref13</id>
      <referenceIdString>b12</referenceIdString>
      <source>E. Harder: Routing and wavelength assignment in all-optical WDM wavelength-routed networks, PhD thesis</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1998</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1998</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref14</id>
      <referenceIdString>b13</referenceIdString>
      <source>R. Ramaswami and K. Sivarajan: Optical communication networks, Morgan-Kaufmann</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>1998</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1998</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref15</id>
      <referenceIdString>b14</referenceIdString>
      <source>Hao: Hybrid Evolutionary Algorithms for Graph Coloring. Journal of Combinatoral Optimization</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>J</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>1999</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1999</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref16</id>
      <referenceIdString>b15</referenceIdString>
      <source>Improvements and comparison of heuristics for solving the multisource Weber problem</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Brimberg</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <note>Operational Research, issue 48</note>
      <pageFrom>444</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>460</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref17</id>
      <referenceIdString>b16</referenceIdString>
      <title>Simha: The Partition Coloring Problem and its Application to Wavelength Routing and Assignment</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the First Workshop on Optical Networks</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>R</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref18</id>
      <referenceIdString>b17</referenceIdString>
      <title>A functional classification of routing and wavelength assignment schemes in DWDM networks: Static case</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Optical Communication and Networks, pages 1109-1115</source>
      <publisher>Paris</publisher>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Choi</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref19</id>
      <referenceIdString>b18</referenceIdString>
      <source>Constructive Genetic Algorithm and Column Generation: an Application to Graph Coloring, paper published on the Internet</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Filho</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref20</id>
      <referenceIdString>b19</referenceIdString>
      <source>T. English: Optimization Is Easy and Learning Is Hard in the Typical Function. Proceedings of the 2000 Congress on Evolutionary Computation: CEC00, pages 924-931</source>
      <authors/>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref21</id>
      <referenceIdString>b20</referenceIdString>
      <title>Hertz: Finding the chromatic number by means of critical graphs</title>
      <source>F. Herrmann and A</source>
      <authors/>
      <note>ACM Journal of Experimental Algorithmics</note>
      <publicationDateString>2002</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2002</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref22</id>
      <referenceIdString>b21</referenceIdString>
      <title>Zufferey: A Variable Neighborhood Search for Graph Coloring</title>
      <source>European Journal of Operational Research, volume 151, pages 379-388</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>A</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Avanthay</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>N</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2003</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2003</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref23</id>
      <referenceIdString>b22</referenceIdString>
      <title>Frota: Cliques, holes and the vertex coloring polytope</title>
      <source>Information Processing Letters, volume 89, pages 159-164</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>M</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Correa</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Y</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2004</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2004</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref24</id>
      <referenceIdString>b23</referenceIdString>
      <title>Correa: On the asymmetric representatives formulation for the vertex coloring problem</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the 2th Brazilian Symposium on Graphs, Algorithms and Combinatorics, volume 19 of Electronic Notes in Discrete Mathematics, pages 337-343</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>V</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Campelo</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>R</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2005</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2005</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref25</id>
      <referenceIdString>b24</referenceIdString>
      <title>Galinier and A. Hertz: Efficient algorithms for finding critical subgraphs</title>
      <source>volume 156, issue 2, pages 244-266</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>P</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Desrosiers</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2005</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2005</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref26</id>
      <referenceIdString>b25</referenceIdString>
      <title>Zufferey: An Adaptive Memory Algorithm for the Graph Coloring Problem</title>
      <source>volume 156, issue 2, pages 267-279</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>P</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Hertz</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>N</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2005</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2005</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref27</id>
      <referenceIdString>b26</referenceIdString>
      <title>Ribeiro: Routing and wavelength assignment by partition colouring</title>
      <source>European Journal of Operational Research</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>C</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2006</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2006</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref28</id>
      <referenceIdString>b27</referenceIdString>
      <title>Zufferey: A graph coloring heuristic using partial solutions and a reactive tabu scheme</title>
      <source>Computers &amp; Operations Research Volume 35, issue 3, pages 960-975</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>N</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2008</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2008</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref29</id>
      <referenceIdString>b28</referenceIdString>
      <title>Variable space search for graph coloring</title>
      <source>Discrete Applied Mathematics</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Hertz</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2008</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2008</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref30</id>
      <referenceIdString>b29</referenceIdString>
      <source>S. Luke: Essentials of Metaheuristics. Lulu</source>
      <authors/>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref31</id>
      <referenceIdString>b30</referenceIdString>
      <source>A branch-and-cut algorithm for partition coloring</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Frota</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <note>Networks, volume 55</note>
      <pageFrom>194</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>204</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2010</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2010</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref32</id>
      <referenceIdString>b31</referenceIdString>
      <source>Instances for the partition Coloring Problem</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Frota</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref33</id>
      <referenceIdString>b32</referenceIdString>
      <source>Safe Lower Bounds For Graph Coloring</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Held</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <pageFrom>261</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>273</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2011</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2011</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref34</id>
      <referenceIdString>b33</referenceIdString>
      <title>Malucelli: Exact Solution of Graph Coloring Problems via Constraint Programming and Column Generation</title>
      <source>INFORMS Journal on Computing</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>F</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2012</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2012</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref35</id>
      <referenceIdString>b34</referenceIdString>
      <title>Raidl: An evolutionary algorithm with solution archive for the generalized minimum spanning tree problem</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on Computer Aided Systems Theory: Part I, volume 6927 of LNCS, pages 287-294</source>
      <publisher>Springer</publisher>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>G</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2012</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2012</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
  </references>
</Publication>