<Publication>
  <id>TUW-223973</id>
  <title>Identifying Condition-Action Sentences Using a Heuristic-based Information Extraction Method Reinhardt Wenzina and Katharina Kaiser Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</title>
  <abstractText>Translating clinical practice guidelines into a computer-inter-pretable format is a challenging and laborious task. In this project we focus on supporting the early steps of the modeling process by automatically identifying conditional activities in guideline documents in order to model them automatically in further consequence. Therefore, we developed a rule-based, heuristic method that combines domain-independent information extraction rules and semantic pattern rules. The classification also uses a weighting coefficient to verify the relevance of the sentence in the context of other information aspects, such as effects, intentions , etc. Our evaluation results show that even with a small set of training data, we achieved a recall of 75 % and a precision of 88 %. This outcome shows that this method supports the modeling task and eases the translation of CPGs into a semi-formal model. Clinical Practice Guidelines (CPGs) are defined as &quot;systematically developed statements to assist practitioners and patient decisions about appropriate health-care for specific circumstances&quot; [6]. They include recommendations describing appropriate care for the management of patients with a specific clinical condition. An important part of CPG contents refers to the procedures to perform, often formulated together with specific conditions that have to hold in order to execute an activity. CPGs are published as textual guidelines, but in order to deploy them in some kind of computerized tool (e.g., a reminder system or a more complex decision-support system) they have to be represented in specialized languages (see [15, 7] for a comparison and overview). Although different authoring/editing tools are often associated with these languages, authoring is a labor-intensive task that requires comprehensive knowledge in medical as well as computer science. There have been several approaches to ease the modeling process, amongst others by introducing intermediate representations that provide more semi-struc-tured and less formal formats. One of them is MHB, the Many-Headed Bridge 2 [21], that tries to bridge the gap between the guideline text and its corresponding formalized model. It falls in the category of document-centric approaches [22] and is devised to produce a non-executable XML document with the relevant CPG fragments, starting from the original text. The knowledge of a CPG is thereby represented in a series of chunks that correspond to a certain bit of information in the CPG (e.g., a sentence, part of a sentence, more than one sentence). The information in a chunk is structured in various dimensions, e.g., control flow, data flow. To additionally support the modeling task for non-IT experts, MHB was further developed and split into MHB-F (free-text version) and MHB-S (semantically enriched version) [19]. MHB-F now provides a very simplified structure to make the modeling even for non-IT experts feasible and to leave modeling details to knowledge engineers in a later step. In order to ease the laborious modeling, parts of the task should be automated by applying information extraction methods. In this work we will focus on the identification of condition-action sentences that form a prominent aspect of the process flow in CPGs. The discovery of such combinations is not a trivial one. On the one hand, condition-action sentences are rarely of the form &apos;if condition then action&apos;, but require more sophisticated identification methods. On the other hand, conditions may refer to effects, intentions, or events and not activities, and these combinations have to be sorted out by our method. Table 1 shows a few example sentences in regard to their MHB-F aspects.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>computer-interpretable clinical guidelines</string>
    <string>medical guide-line formalization</string>
    <string>Many-Headed Bridge (MHB)</string>
    <string>UMLS</string>
    <string>Information Extraction (IE) 1 Introduction</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology Favoritenstrasse</institution>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>sentence</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>clinical activity</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>lished. background information</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>effect</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Background and Related Work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>4</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Methods</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Knowledge Sources and Tools</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.</level>
      <title>The</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>IF</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.0</level>
      <title>3 IF</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1.0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.0</level>
      <title>5 IF</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.0</level>
      <title>6 SHOULD</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>... ...</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>6</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Legend: condition , consequence</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>Generation of the Domain-Dependent Semantic Pattern Set</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>7</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>8</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>* 1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>4+3</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>=</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>7</level>
      <title>.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Evaluation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>9</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>10</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>Conclusions and Further Work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>12</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>