<Publication>
  <id>TUW-201160</id>
  <title>Variable Neighborhood Search for Capacitated Connected Facility Location Markus Leitner and Günther R. Raidl Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</title>
  <note>The Capacitated Connected Facility Location Problem (CConFL) is an N P-</note>
  <abstractText>hard combinatorial optimization problem which arises in the design of last mile communication networks (fiber-to-the-curb scenarios) [1]. Formally, we are given an undirected, weighted graph G = (V, E), with edge costs c e ≥ 0, ∀e ∈ E. The node set V = {r}∪F ∪T is the disjoint union of the root node r, potential facility locations F , and possible Steiner nodes T. Each facility i ∈ F has associated opening costs f i ≥ 0 and a maximum assignable capacity D i ∈ N. Furthermore, we are given a set of potential customers C, with individual capacity demands d k ∈ N and prizes p k ≥ 0, ∀k ∈ C, the latter corresponding to the expected profit when supplying customer k. Each customer k ∈ C may be assigned to one facility of a subset F k ⊆ F , with assignment costs a the set of opened facilities F S ⊆ F and the root node r. C S ⊆ C is the set of customers feasibly (i.e. respecting the capacity constraints) assigned to facilities F S , whereas the actual mapping between customers and facilities is described by α S : C S → F S. The objective value of a feasible solution S is given by c(S) = e∈TS c e + i∈FS f i + k∈CS a αS(k),k + k∈C\CS p k , and we aim to identify a most profitable solution minimizing this function. This variant of CConFL has already been tackled by exact methods based on mixed integer programming [2] and hybrid approaches based on Lagrangian relaxation [1]. Here, we present the first pure metaheuristic approach, which computes high</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology</institution>
          <country>Vienna</country>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Greedy Solution Construction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ˆ ci</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>′</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>General Variable Neighborhood Search</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Greedy Randomized Adaptive Search Procedure</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>Preliminary Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0.01</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0.01</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>