<Publication>
  <id>TUW-233657</id>
  <title>Showing Important Facts to a Critical Audience by Means Beyond Desktop Computing</title>
  <note>Tim Lammarsch, Member, IEEE, Wolfgang Aigner, Member, IEEE, Silvia Miksch, Member, IEEE, Alexander Rind Index Terms-Information Visualization, Visual Analytics, Science Fiction 1 INTRODUCTION</note>
  <abstractText>Recent research in Visualization has focused mostly on data analysis systems for domain experts, but also considered presentation to external people in the form of storytelling. The established directions assume that the target audience has in inherent interest in the facts to be discovered, sometimes even to the point of them being willing to learn how to operate a complex visualization system and spend considerable time and effort. In reality, sometimes the opposite is true: people unwilling to face an inconvenient truth actively avert their eyes. As a solution, we propose the presentation of facts by experts who manage to gain a limited amount of attention by means of rapid and expressive visualization. Using conventional desktop systems, this method is hard to implement, but new visual channels will open up new possibilities. In 1997, Edward Tufte argued that the catastrophic loss of the space shuttle Challenger can be traced back to the engineers who argued for postponing the launch, but failed to convince the officials at NASA [13]. Even though his argument was subject to criticism later [10], the critics refrain &quot;to say that the engineers presentation was not flawed or that even if conceptually correct, could not have been better done&quot; [10]. Both publications are several years old by now, and in the meantime , the science of Visual Analytics has emerged that might have allowed the engineers to gain a much better understanding of their data. Afterward, they might, at best, have made a screenshot from their Visual Analytics system and send that to NASA-active analysis by experts has improved much, but for convincing others, research has stalled. Basically, what Tufte does [13] is nothing else but storytelling [7] which has seen a considerable amount of practical research and is praised as a tool for reporters in writing articles. However, those visu-alizations are still aimed at people of have an active interest in getting information about a topic. The officials at NASA most likely had a high interest of launching the Challenger, and there was only little time to convince them with one or two highly impressive visualizations. In this workshop paper, our intent are to 1. analyze the task of convincing other people by a visualization rather than a lengthy discussion; 2. explain how the emergence of non-desktop (or rather console) computer usage helps in that task; and 3. lay out the prospects for the future. In Section 2, we show what has already been done. In Section 3 we describe three scenarios of a possible future. Finally, in Section 4, [13] E. R. Tufte and E. Weise Moeller. Visual explanations: images and quantities , evidence and narrative, volume 36.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Graphics Press Cheshire</institution>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>RELATED WORK</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>SCENARIOS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>A Day at the Office</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>The Price of a Degree</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>&quot;Working Sucks&quot;</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>REQUIREMENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>