<Publication>
  <id>TUW-138544</id>
  <title>MODELLING OF VISUAL FEATURE DERIVATION IN THE VIZIR FRAMEWORK Horst Eidenberger Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</title>
  <abstractText>If visual information retrieval should make further progress, it will be necessary to identify new ways to derive visual properties from higher levels of understanding than the pixel level (e.g. from low-level features). The paper outlines the implementation of modelling of feature hierarchies in the visual information retrieval framework VizIR (free under GPL). The approach allows for the derivation of high-level features from low-level features by aggregation and localisa-tion as well as semantic enrichment with additional knowledge. The technical implementation is based on the MPEG-7 structures for aggregation and specialisation. 1. INTRODUCTION Visual information retrieval (VIR) research is driven by the desire to derive semantically meaningful information directly from the content of media objects. Recent years have seen considerable efforts to overcome the enormous gravity of the pixel and to extract more than just colour histograms, edge information and other low-level features. The MPEG-7 standard [1] supports these efforts in two ways: Firstly, it provides aggregation and localisation structures for spatio-temporal feature enrichment. Secondly, it standardises cookbooks for the most prominent low-level features and, by that, provides a foundation for semantic enrichment of low-level features. Below, we will regard aggregated/localised and semantically enriched as two relevant types of high-level features. The paper describes the way high-level feature structures (e.g. based on MPEG-7 descriptors) can be implemented in the VIR framework VizIR. The VizIR project [2] aims at providing VIR researchers with a workbench of feature extraction , querying and evaluation tools. The paper is organised as follows: Section 2 gives background information on relevant MPEG-7 models and principles of semantic feature design. Section 3 shortly sketches the VizIR project. Section 4 describes the architecture of high-level feature modelling in VizIR. Additionally, Subsection 4.4 covers important implementation aspects.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology Favoritenstrasse</institution>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Semantic feature enrichment</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.</level>
      <title>BACKGROUND</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>MPEG-7 aggregation and localisation structures</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>THE VIZIR PROJECT</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>Visual feature modelling</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>General framework design</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.</level>
      <title>FEATURE DERIVATION MODELLING</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.1</level>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>DescriptorInfo create DescriptorLogic</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>DescriptorModel use</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>parameterise</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>DescriptorLogicA</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Semantic feature enrichment</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Algorithm Data</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Aggregation / localisation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>DescriptorInfo DescriptorLogic</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>create</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.2</level>
      <title>Feature aggregation and localisation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.3</level>
      <title>Semantic feature enrichment</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.4</level>
      <title>Implementation details</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>