<Publication>
  <id>TUW-141336</id>
  <title></title>
  <abstractText>The QXOR-SAT problem is the quantified version of the satisfiability problem XOR-SAT in which the connective exclusive-or is used instead of the usual or. We study the phase transition associated with random QXOR-SAT instances. We give a description of this phase transition in the case of one alternation of quantifiers, thus performing an advanced practical and theoretical study on the phase transition of a quantified problem. 1. Introduction The last decade has seen a growth of interest in the phase transition for Boolean satisfiability (SAT). The clausal version of this problem shows a sharp transition in the sense that, as the density of clauses is increased, formulas abruptly change from being satisfiable to being unsatisfiable at a critical threshold point. Numerous experimental studies have been performed in the investigation of phase transition for different variants of SAT problems, thus giving strong evidence that the location of the transition coincides with such instances that are hard to solve. In the meantime, theoretical studies have been conducted in order to better understand such transitions. Determining the nature of the phase transition (sharp or coarse) 1 , locating it, determining a precise scaling window and better understanding the structure of the space of solutions turn out to be very challenging tasks, which have aroused a lot of interest in different communities, namely mathematics, computer science and statistical physics (see e.g., Dubois, Monasson, Selman, &amp; Zecchina, 2001). From a computer science point of view, the success of the SAT problem is due to two features. The problem SAT provides a framework in which problems within the complexity class NP can 1. Definitions of sharp and coarse phase transitions can be found on p. 21 in (Janson, Luczak, &amp; Rucinski, 2000). Creignou, Daudé, &amp; Egly be adequately expressed, and moreover practically efficient and highly optimized solvers are available. In order to obtain even stronger systems, many researchers have turned to a powerful generalization of Boolean satisfiability, QSAT, where both universal and existential quan-tifiers over Boolean variables are permitted. The QSAT problem permits the adequate representation and modeling of problems having higher complexity-within the complexity class PSPACE-and coming from various fields of computer science such as knowledge representation , verification and logic. Recently, random instances of these quantified problems have started to attract some attention (see Gent &amp; Walsh, 1999; Chen &amp; Interian, 2005). Models for generating random instances have been developed, and experimental studies have shown that in these models the QSAT property undergoes a phase transition that is qualitatively similar to the one that appears for the ordinary SAT property. As stated by Chen and Interian (2005), the hope is that research on developing competitive solvers for quantified Boolean formulas could benefit from a better understanding of the typical behavior of random instances. Our study follows the pioneering work from Chen and Interian (2005) who have made precise a promising model for generating random instances of the QSAT problem. We use their model and apply it to the satisfiability problem QXOR-SAT that we present below. The difficulty of identifying transition factors and of performing theoretical explorations of the SAT transition has incited many researchers to turn to a variant of the SAT problem: the e-XOR-SAT problem. This satisfiability problem deals with Boolean formulas in con-junctive normal form with e variables per clause, in which the &quot;usual or&quot; is replaced by the &quot;exclusive or&quot; (we call clauses with &quot;exclusive or&quot; as the only connective XOR-clauses). This problem has contributed to develop or validate techniques, thus revealing typical behaviors of both random instances and their space of solutions for SAT-type problems (see, e.g., in order to understand how phase transitions evolve for satisfiability when introducing quantified variables, it is quite natural to consider this problem.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research 29 (2007) 1-18 Submitted 07/06; published 05/07 Phase Transition for Random Quantified XOR-Formulas Nadia Creignou creignou@lifuniv-mrsfr LIF</string>
    <string>UMR CNRS 6166 Université de la Méditerranée 163</string>
    <string>avenue de Luminy 13 288 Marseille</string>
    <string>France Hervé Daudé daude@gyptisuniv-mrsfr LATP</string>
    <string>UMR CNRS 6632 Université de Provence 39</string>
    <string>rue Joliot-Curie 13 453 Marseille</string>
    <string>France Uwe Egly uwe@krtuwienacat Institut für Informationssysteme 184/3 Technische Universität Wien Favoritenstraße 9-11 A-1040 Wien</string>
    <string>Austria</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>Notation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>i=1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Upper</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>The</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Experimental Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>0.9 0.8 0.7 0.6</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 #clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>0.9</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 #clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>Bad</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>a</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>c∈C c∈C</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0.25</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>l</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>u≥1 v≥1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>v≥1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>k=0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>lim</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>x</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 #clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>x</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 #clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.8 0.85</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0.9</level>
      <title>0.95</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>#clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0</level>
      <title>0.8 0.85</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>0.9</level>
      <title>0.95</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>#clauses/#exvars</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>