<Publication>
  <id>TUW-217971</id>
  <title>A Compound Approach for Interactive Visualization of Time-Oriented Data</title>
  <note>Tim Lammarsch * Department of Information and Knowledge Engineering (ike), Danube University Krems, Austria</note>
  <abstractText>Many real-world Visual Analytics applications involve time-oriented data. I am working in a research project related to this challenge where I am responsible for the interactive visualization part. My goal are interactive visualizations to explore such time-oriented data according to the user tasks while considering the structure of time. Time is composed of many granularities that are likely to have crucial influence on the formation of the data. The challenge is to integrate the granularities into a detailed compound view on the data, like the compound eye of insects integrates many images into one view. Other members of our team are experts in temporal data mining and user centered design. The goal is to combine our research topics to an integrated system that helps domain experts to get more insight from their time-oriented data. a natural context, like the change of seasons, they are usually regular , but granularities based on social context can also be irregular, e.g., easter time. They play an important role in many datasets from real-world applications, like customer data from shops.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>1.2</level>
      <title>Interactive Visualization</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>RESEARCH PROBLEMS AND STATE OF THE ART</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.3</level>
      <title>The Visualization Process</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.1</level>
      <title>The Structure of Time</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>RESEARCH QUESTIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6</level>
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>WORK PERFORMED SO FAR</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>NEXT WORKING STEPS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>