<Publication>
  <id>TUW-181199</id>
  <title>spock: A Debugging Support Tool for Logic Programs under the Answer-Set Semantics</title>
  <abstractText>Answer-set programming (ASP) is an emerging logic-programming paradigm that strictly separates the description of a problem from its solving methods. Despite its semantic elegance, ASP suffers from a lack of support for program developers. In particular, tools are needed that help engineers in detecting erroneous parts of their programs. Unlike in other areas of logic programming , applying tracing techniques for debugging logic programs under the answer-set semantics seems rather unnatural, since employing imperative solving algorithms would undermine the declarative flavour of ASP. In this paper, we present the system spock, a debugging support tool for answer-set programs making use of ASP itself. The implemented techniques maintain the declarative nature of ASP within the debugging process and are independent of the actual computation of answer sets. 1 General Information Answer-set programming (ASP) [1] has become an important logic-programming paradigm for declarative problem solving, incorporating fundamental concepts of non-monotonic reasoning. A major reason why ASP has not yet found a more widespread popularity as a problem-solving technique, however, is its lack of suitable engineering tools for developing programs. In particular, realising tools for debugging answer-set programs is a clearly recognised issue in the ASP community, and several approaches in this direction have been proposed in recent years [2-5]. From a theoretical point of view, the nonmonotonicity of answer-set programs is an aggravating factor for detecting sources of errors, since every rule of a program might significantly influence the resulting answer sets. On the other hand, applying tracing techniques for debugging logic programs under the answer-set semantics seems rather unnatural, since employing imperative solving algorithms would undermine the declarative flavour of ASP.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>⋆ Martin Gebser 1</string>
    <string>Jörg Pührer 2</string>
    <string>Torsten Schaub 1</string>
    <string>Hans Tompits 2</string>
    <string>and Stefan Woltran 2 1 Institut für Informatik</string>
    <string>Universität Potsdam</string>
    <string>August-Bebel-Straße 89</string>
    <string>D-14482 Potsdam</string>
    <string>Germany {gebser</string>
    <string>torsten}@csuni-potsdamde 2 Institut für Informationssysteme</string>
    <string>Technische Universität Wien</string>
    <string>Favoritenstraße 9-11</string>
    <string>A-1040 Vienna</string>
    <string>Austria {puehrer</string>
    <string>tompits}@krtuwienacat woltran@dbaituwienacat</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Background</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>Answer-Set Programs</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Tagging-Based Debugging</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Command-Line</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Arguments Input Program</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>&lt;file_1&gt; spock</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Internal</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Program</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Translation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>&lt;file_2&gt;</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Parser</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Program &lt;file_n&gt;</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Representation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>System</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>X</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>+</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>+ 1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>+ 1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Discussion and Related Work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>