<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date>Schiex 2013; Nielsen and Parsons 2007; Nouioua 2013; Polberg and Oren 2014; Brewka and Woltran 2010; Amgoud and Vesic 2011; Bench-Capon 2003; Modgil 2009).</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">Schiex 2013; Nielsen and Parsons 2007; Nouioua 2013; Polberg and Oren 2014; Brewka and Woltran 2010; Amgoud and Vesic 2011; Bench-Capon 2003; Modgil 2009).</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Intertranslatability of Abstract Argumentation Frameworks Sylwia Polberg University College London, United Kingdom</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>argumentation is a rich research subfield of AI and till today, numerous frameworks for it have been proposed. It is thus natural to ask whether one can translate between these structures, and what are the price and consequences of undergoing this process. Although every study explains how a given structure relates to the cornerstone of abstract argu-mentation-Dung&apos;s framework-there are less results available concerning the connections between more advanced formalisms. Moreover, the existing research is not particularly systematized or classified in a way that would clearly show us the properties of a given transformation. In our work, we address these issues by creating an in-depth compendium on the intertranslatability of argumentation frameworks, describing approximately eighty translations. Furthermore, we provide a system for analyzing a given transformation in terms of its functional, syntactical, semantical and computational properties and the underlying methodology. Over the last years, argumentation has become an influential subfield of artificial intelligence, with applications ranging from legal reasoning (Bench-Capon, Prakken, and Sartor 2009) to dialogues and persuasion (McBurney and Parsons 2009; Prakken 2009) to medicine (Fox et al. 2010; Hunter and Williams 2012) to eGovernment (Atkinson, Bench-Capon, and McBurney 2006). Within it, we can distinguish the abstract argumentation approaches, at the heart of which lies Dung&apos;s argumentation framework (Dung 1995). Since the structure itself was relatively limited, as it took into account only the conflict relation between the arguments, it inspired the search for more general models (Brewka, Pol-berg, and Woltran 2014). Throughout the years, many of its extensions were proposed, ranging from the ones employing various strengths and preferences to those that focus on researching new types of relations between arguments (Baroni et al. 2011; Cayrol and Lagasquie-Such an amount of frameworks should not come as a surprise. Argumentation is a wide area with numerous applications , in which one has to face different classes of problems. Frameworks of a given type can be seen as tools to model particular issues and concepts, which on one side gives us more insight into how to approach the problems, but on the other affects the framework&apos;s design. Nevertheless, with so</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>The author is a member of the Vienna PhD School of Infor- matics. This research was funded by project I1102 supported by the Austrian Science Fund FWF. The author is currently supported by EPSRC Project EP/N008294/1 "Framework for Computational Persuasion".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head><p>Amgoud, L., and Vesic, S. 2011. A new approach for preference-based argumentation frameworks. Annals of Mathematics and Artificial <ref type="bibr">Intelligence 63:149-183. Atkinson, K.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Bench-Capon, T. J. M.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and McBurney, P. 2006. PARMENIDES:</ref> Facilitating deliberation in democ- racies. Artificial Intelligence and Law 14 <ref type="bibr">(4):261-275. Baroni, P.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Cerutti, F.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Giacomin, M.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Guida, G. 2011. AFRA:</ref> Argumentation framework with recursive attacks. International Journal of Approximate Reasoning 52 <ref type="bibr">(1):1937. Bench-Capon, T. J. M.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Prakken, H.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Sartor, G. 2009.</ref> Argumentation in legal reasoning. In Simari, G., and Rahwan, I., eds., Argumentation in Artificial Intelligence. <ref type="bibr">Springer. 363-382.</ref> Bench-Capon, T. J. M. 2003. Persuasion in practical argu- ment using value-based argumentation frameworks. Journal of Logic and Computation 13 <ref type="bibr">(3):429-448. Brewka, G., and Woltran, S. 2010. Abstract Dialectical Frameworks. In Lin, F.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sattler, U.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Truszczynski, M., eds.</ref>, Proceedings of the Twelfth International Conference on Principles of Knowledge Representation and Reasoning, KR</p><note type="other">2010. Toronto, Ontario, Canada: AAAI Press. Brewka, G.; Ellmauthaler, S.; Strass, H.; Wallner, J. P.; and Woltran, S. 2013. Abstract Dialectical Frameworks Re- visited. In Rossi, F., ed., Proceedings of the 23rd Inter- national Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence, IJCAI 2013, 803-809. Beijing, China: AAAI Press / IJCAI. Brewka, G.; Polberg, S.; and Woltran, S. 2014. Generaliza- tions of Dung frameworks and their role in formal argumen- tation. Intelligent Systems, IEEE 29(1):30-38. Cayrol, C., and Lagasquie-Schiex, M.-C. 2009. Bipolar ab- stract argumentation systems. In Simari, G., and Rahwan, I., eds., Argumentation in Artificial Intelligence. Springer. 65- 84. Cayrol, C., and Lagasquie-Schiex, M.-C. 2013. Bipolarity in argumentation graphs: Towards a better understanding. In- ternational Journal of Approximate Reasoning 54(7):876- 899.</note><p>Dung, P. M. 1995. On the acceptability of arguments and its fundamental role in nonmonotonic reasoning, logic programming and n-person games. <ref type="bibr">Artificial Intelligence 77:321-357. Dunne, P. E.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Dvok, W.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Linsbichler, T.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Woltran, S. 2015.</ref> Characteristics of multiple viewpoints in abstract ar- gumentation. <ref type="bibr">Artificial Intelligence 228:153 -178. Dyrkolbotn, S. K. 2014.</ref> How to argue for anything: En- forcing arbitrary sets of labellings using afs. In Principles of Knowledge Representation and Reasoning: Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference, <ref type="bibr">KR 2014</ref><ref type="bibr">, Vienna, Austria, July 20-24, 2014</ref><ref type="bibr">Gaggl, S. A.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Woltran, S. 2010</ref>. Answer-set programming encodings for argumentation frameworks. Ar- gument and <ref type="figure">Computation 1(2):147-177</ref>. Ellmauthaler, S., and Strass, H. 2014. The DIAMOND sys- tem for computing with abstract dialectical frameworks. <ref type="bibr">In Parsons, S.; Oren, N.; Reed, C.; and Cerutti, F., eds., Inter</ref> national Conference on Computational Models of Argument <ref type="bibr">(COMMA 2014)</ref>, volume 266 of Frontiers in Artificial Intel- ligence and <ref type="bibr">Applications, 233-240. IOS Press. Fox, J.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Glasspool, D.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Patkar, V.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Austin, M.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Black, L.;</ref><ref type="bibr">South, M.;</ref><ref type="bibr">Robertson, D.;</ref><ref type="bibr">and Vincent, C. 2010.</ref> Delivering clinical decision support services: There is nothing as prac- tical as a good theory. Journal of Biomedical Informatics 43 <ref type="bibr">(5):831-843. Hunter, A., and Williams, M. 2012</ref>. Aggregating evidence about the positive and negative effects of treatments. Artifi- cial Intelligence in <ref type="figure">Medicine 56(3):173-190</ref>. McBurney, P., and Parsons, S. 2009. Dialogue games for agent argumentation. In Simari, G., and Rahwan, I., eds., Argumentation in Artificial Intelligence. <ref type="bibr">Springer. 261-280.</ref> Modgil, S., and Bench-Capon, T. J. M. 2011. Metalevel ar- gumentation. Journal of Logic and Polberg, S., and Oren, N. 2014. Revisiting support in abstract argumentation systems. In Parsons, S.; Oren, N.; Reed, C.; and Cerutti, F., eds., Computational Models of Argument -Proceedings of COMMA 2014, volume 266 of Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence and Applications, 369- 376. IOS Press. Prakken, H. 2009. Models of persuasion dialogue. In Simari, G., and Rahwan, I., eds., Argumentation in Artificial Intelli- gence. Springer. 281-301.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
