<Publication>
  <id>TUW-245336</id>
  <title>Inscribing Futures through Responsible Design by Responsible Designers</title>
  <abstractText>As technology designers, we often inadvertently inscribe values and concepts in systems beyond what we intended. Further, while we aim to work from a user-and use-centred perspective, we often miss the perspectives of other critical stakeholders and the broader context in which technology systems are to be used. Reflecting on issues of responsible innovation from the bottom up, this paper explores two exemplar cases: designing for older people and health care agendas, and designing for eco-behaviour change agendas. While very different in focus, both highlight the importance that different conceptualisations have on shaping possible solutions, and the challenge of identifying and negotiating competing agendas. This draws attention to the limits of both top-down and bottom-up perspectives and suggests instead a middle out approach to responsible design that considers both policy and practice aspects in the process. It also calls for us as responsible designers to be reflective practitioners aware of our power in inscribing possible futures. 1 Introduction Human Computer Interaction (HCI) as a field is concerned with the design of technologies from a user-and use-centred perspective, to ensure that technologies are not only easy to use but are also useful, meet real needs and fit into people&apos;s everyday lives and practices. This is especially important as we move from applications focused on the desktop and the workplace to considering technologies embedded in everyday life. Technology is everywhere now and touches on all spheres of life, not just for work and efficiency, but for how we play, create, relate, socialise, and so on. As noted by Sellen et al. (2009), technology in this new pervasive and mobile world is fundamentally shaping what it means to be human. As such, we are inscribing futures, intended and unintended, through our technology design. This places a huge responsibility on researchers and designers to design technologies in a responsible way; this is a quantum step away from just designing elements of an</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Geraldine</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Fitzpatrick</lastName>
      <affiliations/>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Responsible sustainability: food waste</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>7</level>
      <title>Aarhus</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>