<Publication>
  <id>TUW-174216</id>
  <title></title>
  <abstractText>During the last decades, digital objects have become the primary medium to create, shape, and exchange information. However, in contrast to analog objects such as books that directly represent their content, digital objects are not usable without a corresponding technical environment. The fast changes in these environments and in formats and technologies mean that digital documents have a short lifespan before they become obsolete. Digital preservation, i.e. actions to ensure longevity of digital information, thus has become a pressing challenge. The dominant strategies prevailing today are migration and emulation; for each strategy, different tools are available. When converting an object to a different representation, a validation of the content is needed to verify that the transformed objects are still authentically representing the same intellectual content. This validation so far is largely done manually, which is infeasible for large collections. Preservation planning supports decision makers in reaching accountable decisions by evaluating potential strategies against well-defined requirements. Especially the evaluation of different migration tools for digital preservation has to rely on validating the converted objects and thus on an analysis of the logical structure and the content of documents. Existing approaches for characterising and describing objects do not attempt to fully extract the informational content of digital objects and thus are not suffficient for an in-depth validation of transformed content. This paper describes the eXtensible Characterisation Languages (XCL) that support the automatic validation of document conversions and the evaluation of migration quality by hierarchically decomposing a document and representing documents from different sources in an abstract XML language. The description language XCDL provides an abstract representation of digital content in XML, while the extraction language XCEL allows an extraction engine to create such an abstract description by mapping file format structures to XCDL concepts. We present the context of the development of these languages and tools and describe the overall concept and features of the languages. We further give examples and show how the languages can be applied to the evaluation of digital preservation solutions in the context of preservation planning. The last decades have made digital objects the primary medium to create, shape, and exchange information. An increasing part of our cultural and scientific heritage is being created and maintained in digital form; digital content is at the heart of today&apos;s economy, and its ubiquity is increasingly shaping private lives. The ever-growing complexity and heterogeneity of digital file formats together with rapid changes in underlying technologies have posed extreme challenges to the longevity of information. So far, digital objects are inherently ephemeral. Memory institutions such as national libraries and archives were amongst the first to approach the problem of ensuring long-term access to digital objects when the original software or hardware to interpret them correctly becomes unavailable [UNESCO, 2003]. Digital preservation denotes the efforts to preserve digital objects for a given purpose over long periods of time. The urgency of digital preservation has recently been reemphasised by the results of a survey among archiving professionals [The 100 Year Archive Task Force, 2007]. In the last years, numerous research initiatives have started around the world that aim at mastering this challenge. The two strategies generally considered to prevail today are migration[Testbed, 2001; Mellor et al., 2002] and emulation[Rothenberg, 1999; van der Hoeven and van Wijngaarden, 2005]. Migration, the conversion of a digital object to another representation, is the most widely applied solution for standard object types such as electronic documents or images. The critical problem generally is how to ensure consistency and authenticity and preserve all the essential features and the conceptual characteristics of the original object whilst transforming its logical representation. Lawrence et. al. presented different kinds of risks for a migration project [Lawrence et al., 2000]. While migration operates on the objects and transforms them to more stable or more widely adopted representations, em-ulation operates on the environment of an object, trying to simulate the original environment that the object needs. Consider a large collection of documents written in an old version of Word several years ago. This application does not run on modern operating systems. One could try to emulate the original operating system; but the emulation software still depends on current hardware, and emulating the hardware might be even harder. On the other hand, one could also migrate the documents to a current version of Word, or to PDF. While this would lose the original look-and-feel of the application, it would probably preserve the content and layout. With PDF, one would exchange the tool support provided by text processing software, as well as metadata such as an edit history, for a file format that is generally considered to be quite stable. An important part of ongoing efforts in many large international projects is</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>UCS Systematic Characterisation of Objects in Digital Preservation: The eXtensible Characterisation Languages Christoph Becker</string>
    <string>Andreas Rauber (Vienna University of Technology</string>
    <string>Austria {becker</string>
    <string>rauber}@ifstuwienacat) Volker Heydegger</string>
    <string>Jan Schnasse</string>
    <string>Manfred Thaller (University of Cologne</string>
    <string>Germany {herrmanv</string>
    <string>janschnasse</string>
    <string>manfredthaller}@uni-koelnde) Key Words: Digital Libraries</string>
    <string>Digital Preservation</string>
    <string>Preservation Planning</string>
    <string>Content Characterisation</string>
    <string>Migration</string>
    <string>XML languages</string>
    <string>Evaluation</string>
    <string>File formats</string>
    <string>File conversion</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Information Storage and Retrieval -Digital Libraries Document and Text Processing Becker</institution>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>2938</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2939</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Related work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2940</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2941</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2942</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>The extraction language XCEL</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2944</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>The description language XCDL</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2945</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2947</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.4</level>
      <title>Comparing digital objects</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2948</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.5</level>
      <title>Summary</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Summary and Outlook</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2949</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2950</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2952</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>