<Publication>
  <id>TUW-255712</id>
  <title></title>
  <note>Intertranslatability of Abstract Argumentation Frameworks Sylwia Polberg University College London, United Kingdom</note>
  <abstractText>argumentation is a rich research subfield of AI and till today, numerous frameworks for it have been proposed. It is thus natural to ask whether one can translate between these structures, and what are the price and consequences of undergoing this process. Although every study explains how a given structure relates to the cornerstone of abstract argu-mentation-Dung&apos;s framework-there are less results available concerning the connections between more advanced formalisms. Moreover, the existing research is not particularly systematized or classified in a way that would clearly show us the properties of a given transformation. In our work, we address these issues by creating an in-depth compendium on the intertranslatability of argumentation frameworks, describing approximately eighty translations. Furthermore, we provide a system for analyzing a given transformation in terms of its functional, syntactical, semantical and computational properties and the underlying methodology. Over the last years, argumentation has become an influential subfield of artificial intelligence, with applications ranging from legal reasoning (Bench-Capon, Prakken, and Sartor 2009) to dialogues and persuasion (McBurney and Parsons 2009; Prakken 2009) to medicine (Fox et al. 2010; Hunter and Williams 2012) to eGovernment (Atkinson, Bench-Capon, and McBurney 2006). Within it, we can distinguish the abstract argumentation approaches, at the heart of which lies Dung&apos;s argumentation framework (Dung 1995). Since the structure itself was relatively limited, as it took into account only the conflict relation between the arguments, it inspired the search for more general models (Brewka, Pol-berg, and Woltran 2014). Throughout the years, many of its extensions were proposed, ranging from the ones employing various strengths and preferences to those that focus on researching new types of relations between arguments (Baroni et al. 2011; Cayrol and Lagasquie-Such an amount of frameworks should not come as a surprise. Argumentation is a wide area with numerous applications , in which one has to face different classes of problems. Frameworks of a given type can be seen as tools to model particular issues and concepts, which on one side gives us more insight into how to approach the problems, but on the other affects the framework&apos;s design. Nevertheless, with so</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>