<Publication>
  <id>TUW-225252</id>
  <title>Reconstructing Cross Cut Shredded Documents with a Genetic Algorithm with Solution Archive</title>
  <note>Benjamin Biesinger, Christian Schauer, Bin Hu, and Günther R. Raidl</note>
  <abstractText>The reconstruction of shredded documents is of high interest not only in forensic science but also when documents are destroyed unintentionally. Reconstructing cross-cut shredded documents (RCCSTD) is particularly difficult since the documents are cut into rectangular pieces of equal size. Since shape information along the edges-in contrast to hand torn pieces-cannot be exploited, the reconstruction solely depends on the information written on the shreds. Therefore, we use a metric for calculating the number of gray value mismatches along the edges of two shreds put next to each other either horizontally or vertically. Consequentially, we model the document reconstruction as a combinatorial optimization problem minimizing the overall mismatch of the reconstructed document. Since we focus in this work on the combinatorial aspect of the problem we use this simple metric which can be replaced in future work by more advanced pattern recognition techniques, see [2] for a sample method. In previous work, Prandtstetter and Raidl [3] developed an Ant Colony Optimization and a Variable Neighborhood Search (VNS) for the RCCSTD, while Schauer et al. [5] proposed a Memetic Algorithm (MA). Sleit et al. [6] proposed a different approach by iteratively merging two clusters that fit together well and repairing possibly occurring conflicts. In this work the MA from [5] is adapted and extended by a complete solution archive in order to avoid duplicate solutions by efficiently storing all visited solutions in a special data structure. If a duplicate solution is detected it is converted into a similar yet unconsidered one. This is done to preserve the diversity of the population and to avoid unnecessary re-evaluations of already visited solutions. This approach is a rather new method for duplicate detection and conversion which was successfully applied on several binary problems (e.g., MAX-SAT) in [4] as well as on the generalized minimum spanning tree problem [1]. 2 A Genetic Algorithm with Solution Archive For a detailed description of the GA and its operators, which is extended by our solution archive, see [5]. To encode solutions the authors used an n×n array that</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms Vienna University of Technology Favoritenstrae 911/1861</string>
    <string>1040 Vienna</string>
    <string>Austria {biesinger|schauer|hu|raidl}@adstuwienacat 1 Introduction</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Results and Conclusions</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>