<Publication>
  <id>TUW-191715</id>
  <title>CURRENT TRENDS IN COMPUTER GRAPHICS BY WERNER PURGATHOFER* and ROBERT F. TOBLER**</title>
  <note>BULETINUL INSTITUTULUI POLITEHNIC DIN IAŞI Publicat de Universitatea Tehnică &quot;Gheorghe Asachi&quot; din Iaşi Tomul LVI (LX), Fasc. 2, 2010 Secţia AUTOMATICĂ şi CALCULATOARE</note>
  <abstractText>In this paper we give an overview of the current research trends and explore the challenges in several subfields of the scientific discipline of computer graphics: interactive and photorealistic rendering, scientific and information visualization, and visual analytics. Five challenges are extracted that play a role in each of these areas: scalability, semantics, fusion, interaction, acquisition. Of course, not all of these issues are disjunct to each other, however the chosen structure allows for a easy to follow overview of the concrete future challenges. Computer graphics studies methods for producing digital images of data with the goal to communicate computer output to a human user in the form of pictures. The visual input channel has by far the broadest bandwidth of all our senses and therefore enables the most effective transport of information from computers to humans. Production includes synthesizing, manipulating and displaying the underlying data. The data may be almost any content one can think of: geometric or other spatial data just as well as statistical data, simulation results or abstract data, all real or virtual. Roughly speaking, the ultimate goal of rendering research is to create perfectly realistic looking real-time images of real-world objects, whereas visualization tries to create images of data and structures that are otherwise invisible to the human eye or completely abstract. 10 Werner Purgathofer and Robert F. Tobler Computer graphics has been among the most successful computer science fields during the last three decades and the methods and results available today have exceeded the expectations by far. Therefore some people consider most computer graphics problems as solved, providing a ready to use set of tools for applications. But while this is true for some areas with simple use of computer images, the embedding of computer graphics technology in increasingly complex surroundings generates many new challenges. Usage of computer graphics is embedded in more and more complicated environments, making its combined use with other technologies more and more natural, so that many people talk about disciplines growing together. Such fields are computer vision, image processing, pattern recognition, tracking, scanning, video augmentation, information theory, user interface design, large data bases and several more. Multiple articles in the past decades have extracted future research problems in various subfields of computer graphics, e.g. [1],…,[3]. In this article we will describe the research trends of the coming years based on five major challenges that are common to all computer graphics sub-fields. These are: 1. Scalability = how to cope with huge amounts of data, highly parallel computers and distributed devices. 2. Semantics = how can meaning be extracted from data and context and be used for better insight. 3. Fusion = how can multiple techniques, data streams, and models be combined to solve complex problems. 4. Interaction = how to combine multiple and ubiquitous input devices to create ergonomic user interfaces. 5. Acquisition = how can data from various input sources be processed to deal with missing data, contradictions, and uncertainty. These challenges are often interdependent to some degree. For example, semantics can assist scalability by determining features that can be left away at a given level of detail, and acquisition by allowing a meaningful extrapolation of missing data and resolution of contradictions; petascale data will require new interaction metaphors and acquisition and data processing methods. Consequently, any research in these areas will typically cross boundaries and cannot be strictly attributed to a single challenge. Still, this discrimination facilitates the following description of the specific aspects of each challenge. 2. Scalability 2.1. Challenges in Scalability The challenges posed by the enormous amount of data generated by</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>computer graphics</string>
    <string>rendering</string>
    <string>visualization</string>
    <string>challenges</string>
    <string>computer vision 2000 Mathematics Subject Classification: 68-02</string>
    <string>68U05 1 Introduction</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>2, 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>11</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>12</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.3.</level>
      <title>Scalability Challenges in Rendering and Virtual Reality</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2, 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>13</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>Semantics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1.</level>
      <title>Challenges in Semantics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>14</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2.</level>
      <title>Semantics Challenges in Visualization and Visual Analytics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3.</level>
      <title>Semantics Challenges in Rendering and Virtual Reality</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2, 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>15</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.</level>
      <title>Fusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.1.</level>
      <title>Challenges in Fusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>16</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.2.</level>
      <title>Fusion Challenges in Visualization and Visual Analytics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.3.</level>
      <title>Fusion Challenges in Rendering and Virtual Reality</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>Interaction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.1.</level>
      <title>Challenges in Interaction</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>17</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.2.</level>
      <title>Interaction Challenges in Visualization and Visual Analytics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>18</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.3.</level>
      <title>Interaction Challenges in Rendering and Virtual Reality</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6.</level>
      <title>Acquisition</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6.1.</level>
      <title>Challenges in Acquisition</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6.2.</level>
      <title>Acquisition Challenges in Visualization and Visual Analytics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>20</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6.3.</level>
      <title>Acquisition Challenges in Rendering and Virtual Reality</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2, 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>21</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>7.</level>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Received: April 12, 2010 *Vienna University of Technology, Institute of Computer Graphics and</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>Johnson C., Top Scientific Visualization Research Problems. IEEE Computer</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>22</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>* * VRVis</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>A Multiresolution Mesh Generation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>24</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>