<Publication>
  <id>TUW-197852</id>
  <title>Women in Technology Program of the Vienna University of Technology, and the Austrian Federal Ministry of Science and Research</title>
  <abstractText>are introduced to this diagram, they often have to solve exercises where texts in natural language are given and they have to model the described systems. When analyzing such exercises, it becomes evident that certain kinds of phrases describing a particular concept appear again and again contextualized to the described domain. In this paper, we present an approach which allows the automatic generation of tex-tual specifications from a given Class Diagram based on standard phrases in natural language. Besides supporting teachers in preparing exercises, such an approach is also valuable for various e-learning scenarios. Keywords: modeling exercises, natural language description 1 Introduction When teaching modeling, one of the most repetitive and time consuming tasks is the development of exercises and the corresponding solutions. A typical exercise consists of a given textual description of an arbitrary domain (e.g., university systems, enterprises, airports) which students have to model for example with a UML Class Diagram. In order to obtain an adequate exercise, it does not suffice to prepare the textual specification only, but also the sample solution has to be modeled for checking if all taught concepts are covered and if the difficulty level and size are reasonable. Hence, the teacher has to describe the same content twice: once as textual specification in natural language and once as a model. As there should be a one-to-one correspondence between text and model, the question at hand is if it is possible to automatically derive one artifact from the other. Already in the early 1980s attempts of automated translation of textual descriptions into program code were conducted. R.J. Abbott [Abb83] discusses a method for deriving programming concepts like data types and references by analyzing informal English descriptions. An important remark of Abbott&apos;s work relates to the automation level of such a method. He points out that such a transformation is far away from being fully automated. User interaction is still needed * Funding for this research was provided by the fFORTE WIT</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>Electronic Communications of the EASST Volume 34 (2010) Proceedings of the 6th Educators&apos; Symposium: Software Modeling in Education at MODELS 2010 (EduSymp 2010) Position Paper: m2n-A Tool for Translating Models to Natural Language Descriptions Petra Brosch and Andrea Randak 8 pages Guest Editors: Peter J Clarke</string>
    <string>Martina Seidl Managing Editors: Tiziana Margaria</string>
    <string>Julia Padberg</string>
    <string>Gabriele Taentzer ECEASST Home Page: http://wwweasstorg/eceasst/ ISSN 1863-2122 ECEASST Position Paper: m2n-A Tool for Translating Models to Natural Language Descriptions Petra Brosch * and Andrea Randak lastname@bigtuwienacat</string>
    <string>http://wwwbigtuwienacat Business Informatics Group Vienna University of Technology</string>
    <string>Austria Abstract: To describe the structure of a system</string>
    <string>the UML Class Diagram yields the means-of-choice Therefor</string>
    <string>the Class Diagram provides concepts like class</string>
    <string>at-tribute</string>
    <string>operation</string>
    <string>association</string>
    <string>generalization</string>
    <string>aggregation</string>
    <string>enumeration</string>
    <string>etc When students</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Background</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ECEASST</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Traversal Strategy ECORE MM Sentences</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Natural</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Language Description</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>m2n</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Realization</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>8</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>9</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>10</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>11</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>12</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>}</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>14</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>16</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>17</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>18</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>19</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>20</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>21</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>22</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>23</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>24</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>The Long-Term Vision</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.1</level>
      <title>Motivation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Proc. EduSymp 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ECEASST</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.2</level>
      <title>The Basic Architecture</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.3</level>
      <title>The Role of m2n</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Proc. EduSymp 2010</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Bibliography</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>