<Publication>
  <id>TUW-141065</id>
  <title>Analysing the Relationship between Learning Styles and Cognitive Traits</title>
  <abstractText>The need to provide more holistic adaptivity to students has brought us to investigate the relationship between learning styles and working memory capacity (WMC). The aim of this investigation is to study the relationship between learning styles and WMC in order to get additional information about the students. This information can be used to make more holistic adaptivity possible by improving the student modelling process of both learning styles and WMC. An experiment with 297 participants was conducted. Findings suggest that relationships from WMC to the active/reflective, the sensing/intuitive, and the visual/verbal learning styles exist, whereas the suggested relationship from WMC to sequential/global learning styles could not be found. 1. Introduction Providing courses that fit the needs of learners makes learning easier for students. In recent years, researchers focused on the impact of individual characteristics such as learning styles and cognitive traits in technology enhanced learning and how such differences can be incorporated in order to provide adaptive courses. To be able to provide proper adaptivity, the needs of students have to be known first. With respect to technology enhanced learning, Brusilovsky [1] distinguished between two different ways for getting information about the learners&apos; needs: the collaborative and the automatic student modelling approach. In the former, the students explicitly provide information about themselves (e.g. filling out a questionnaire), whereas in the latter, the system infers the needs from the behaviour and actions of the students automatically while they are working/learning in the system. The automatic approach is direct and is free from the problem of inaccurate self-conceptions of students. However, a problem with the automatic approach is to get enough reliable information to build a robust student model. As a solution, Brusilovsky [1] recommended the use of additional sources of information. Hence, it is beneficial to find mechanisms that use whatever information about the learner is already available to get as much reliable information to build a more robust student model. In this paper, we investigate the relationship between learning styles, in particular the Felder-Silverman learning style model (FSLSM) [2], and working memory capacity (WMC). WMC is one of the cognitive traits included in the model to profile students&apos; cognitive traits using student behaviour. The found relationship can then be used to strengthen the inference procedure of student models such as the CTM by including additional information from learning styles. Similarly, the findings can also be used to strength a learning style model which is built not from a questionnaire but from student behaviour observations.</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>* Sabine Graf 1</string>
    <string>Taiyu Lin 2</string>
    <string>Kinshuk 3 1 Vienna University of Technology</string>
    <string>Women&apos;s Postgraduate College for Internet Technologies</string>
    <string>Austria</string>
    <string>sabinegraf@ieeeorg 2 Massey University</string>
    <string>Department of Information Systems</string>
    <string>New Zealand</string>
    <string>taiyulin@gmailcom 3 Athabasca University</string>
    <string>School of Computing and Information Systems</string>
    <string>Canada</string>
    <string>kinshuk@ieeeorg Abstract *</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Cognitive Trait Model</institution>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2.</level>
      <title>Background</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>* This research has been funded partly by the Austrian Federal Ministry for Education, Science, and Culture, the European Social Fund (ESF) under grant 31.963/46-VII/9/2002.</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.</level>
      <title>Method for statistical data analysis</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.</level>
      <title>Materials</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.</level>
      <title>Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.1.</level>
      <title>Measures of Web-OSPAN</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.2.</level>
      <title>Active/reflective dimension</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.3.</level>
      <title>Sensing/intuitive dimension</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.4.</level>
      <title>Visual/verbal dimension</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>7.</level>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5.5.</level>
      <title>Sequential/global dimension</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6.</level>
      <title>Conclusion and future work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>