<Publication>
  <id>TUW-180162</id>
  <title></title>
  <note>Removing Web Spam Links from Search Engine Results Manuel Egele Technical University Vienna pizzaman@iseclab.org Christopher Kruegel University of California Santa Barbara chris@cs.ucsb.edu Engin Kirda Institute Eurecom France kirda@eurecom.fr</note>
  <abstractText>Web spam denotes the manipulation of web pages with the sole intent to raise their position in search engine rankings. Since a better position in the rankings directly and positively affects the number of visits to a site, attackers use different techniques to boost their pages to higher ranks. In the best case, web spam pages are a nuisance that provide undeserved advertisement revenues to the page owners. In the worst case, these pages pose a threat to Internet users by hosting malicious content and launching drive-by attacks against unsuspecting victims. When successful, these drive-by attacks then install malware on the victims&apos; machines. In this paper, we introduce an approach to detect web spam pages in the list of results that are returned by a search engine. In a first step, we determine the importance of different page features to the ranking in search engine results. Based on this information, we develop a classification technique that uses important features to successfully distinguish spam sites from legitimate entries. By removing spam sites from the results, more slots are available to links that point to pages with useful content. Additionally, and more importantly, the threat posed by malicious web sites can be mitigated, reducing the risk for users to get infected by malicious code that spreads via drive-by attacks. 1 Introduction Search engines are designed to help users find relevant information on the Internet. Typically, a user submits a query (i.e., a set of keywords) to a search engine, which then returns a list of links to pages that are most relevant to this query. To determine the most-relevant pages, a search engine selects a set of candidate pages that contain some or all of the query terms and calculates a page score for each page. Finally, a list of pages, sorted by their score, is returned to the user. This score is calculated from properties of the candidate pages, so-called features. Unfortunately, details on the exact algorithms that calculate these ranking values are kept secret by search engine companies, since this information directly influences the quality of the search results. Only general information is made available. For example, in 2007, Google claimed to take more than 200 features into account for the ranking value [8]. The way in which pages are ranked directly influences the set of pages that are visited frequently by the search engine users. The higher a page is ranked, the more likely it is to be visited [3]. This makes search engines an attractive target for everybody who aims to attract a large number of visitors to her site. There are three categories of web sites that benefit directly from high rankings in search engine results. First, sites that sell products or services. In their context, more visitors imply more potential customers. The second category contains sites that are financed through advertisement. These sites aim to rank high for any query. The reason is that they can display their advertisements to each visitor, and, in turn, charge the advertiser. The third, and most dangerous, category of sites that aim to attract many visitors by ranking high in search results are sites that distribute malicious software. Such sites typically contain code that exploits web browser vulnerabilities to silently install malicious software on the visitor&apos;s computer. Once infected, the attacker can steal sensitive information (such as passwords, financial information, or web-banking credentials), misuse the user&apos;s bandwidth to join a denial of service attack, or send spam. The threat of drive-by downloads (i.e., automatically down-loading and installing software without the user&apos;s consent as the result of a mere visit to a web page) and distribution of malicious software via web sites has become a significant security problem. Web sites that host drive-by downloads are either created solely for the purpose of distributing malicious software or existing pages that are hacked and modified (for example, by inserting an iframe tag into the page that loads malicious content). Provos et al. [13, 14] observe that such attacks can quickly reach a large number of potential victims, as at least 1.3% of all search queries directed to the Google search engine contain results that link to malicious pages. Moreover, the pull-based infection scheme circumvents barriers (such as web proxies or NAT devices) that protect from push-based malware infection schemes (such as traditional, exploit-based worms). As a result, the manipulation of search engine results is an attractive technique for attackers that aim to attract victims to their malicious sites and spread malware via drive-by attacks [16]. Search engine optimization (SEO) companies offer their expertise to help clients improve the rank for a given site through a mixture of techniques, which can be classified as being acceptable or malicious. Acceptable techniques refer to approaches that improve the content or the presentation of a page to the benefit of users. Malicious techniques, on the other hand, do not benefit the user but aim to mislead the search engine&apos;s ranking algorithm. The fact that bad sites can be pushed into undeserved, higher ranks via malicious SEO techniques leads to the problem of web spam. Gyöngyi and Garcia-Molina [9] define web spam as every deliberate human action that is meant to improve a site&apos;s ranking without changing the site&apos;s true value. Search engines need to adapt their ranking algorithms continuously to mitigate the effect of spamming techniques on their results. For example, when the Google search engine was launched, it strongly relied on the PageRank [2] algorithm to determine the ranking of a page where the rank is proportional to the number of incoming links. Unfortunately, this led to the problem of link farms and &quot;Google Bombs,&quot; where enormous numbers of automatically created forum posts and blog comments were used to promote an attacker&apos;s target page by linking to it. Clearly, web spam is undesirable, because it degrades the quality of search results and draws users to malicious sites. Although search engines invest a significant amount of money and effort into fighting this problem, checking the results of search engines for popular search terms demonstrates that the problem still exists. In this work, we aim to post-process results returned by a search engine to identify entries that link to spam pages. To this end, we first study the importance of different features for the ranking of a page. In some sense, we attempt to reverse-engineer the &quot;secret&quot; ranking algorithm of a search engine to understand better what features are important. Based on this analysis, we attempt to build a classifier that inspects these features to identify indications that a page is web spam. When such a page is identified, we can remove it from the search results. The two main contributions of this paper are the following: • We conducted comprehensive experiments to understand the effects of different features on search engine rankings.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors/>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.1</level>
      <title>Inferring Important Features</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2.2</level>
      <title>Removing Spam from Search Engine Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>Feature Inference</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.1</level>
      <title>Feature Selection</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>2</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>3</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>4</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>5</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>6</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>7</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>8</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>9</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.2</level>
      <title>Preparation of Pages</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.3</level>
      <title>Execution of Experiments and Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.4</level>
      <title>Extraction of Important Features</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>n</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>f</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>k</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>m</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>k=1</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>60</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>50</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>40</level>
      <title>30</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Distance</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>20</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>10</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>0</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>10</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>15</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>20</level>
      <title>25 30</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>Reducing Spam from Search Engine Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.1</level>
      <title>Detecting Web Spam in Search Engine Results</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.2</level>
      <title>Evaluation</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Classified as Spam Classified as Legitimate</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Spam</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>21</level>
      <title>38</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Legitimate 20 173</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>Related Work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6</level>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Appendix B: List of Experiments</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>No. Feature Combination</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>