<Publication>
  <id>TUW-204724</id>
  <title></title>
  <note>Justyna Patalas-Maliszewska Dr., University of Zielona Góra, Poland/</note>
  <abstractText>The author&apos;s software system for planning and selection of personnel in SME Abstract: The strategic management of intellectual capital involves rethinking how the companies creates value from a knowledge -centric perspective and redesigning and orchestrating the role of staff knowledge in the firm&apos;s strategy. This paper presents the author&apos;s software system for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge. This software is a computer implementation of the method for planning and selection of personnel in SME. information systems that support knowledge management in SMEs can give guarantees a constant competitive advantage in the market. Keywords: intellectual capital, strategic knowledge management 1. Introduction The advantage of a company in the SME sector (small and medium sizes enterprises) is determined by effectiveness and the extent of the knowledge-workers&apos; involvement. The role of intellectual capital management consists in striving to increase the share of immaterial resources (at the costs of the material ones) in the generated products, services, and the total market value of an organization (Król and Ludwiczyński, 2007). The article presents the description of strategic knowledge resources in companies and author&apos;s method for plannig and selection of personnel in SME (see chapter 2). In the third chapter the author&apos;s software system for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge is presented on example of the decision-making situation in which an innovative SME is considering the employment of a new m-th employee. The summary shows the</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames/>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology</institution>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>•</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>•</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Stage 2:</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Stage 3:</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Stage 4:</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>m4</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4.</level>
      <title>Conclusion and direction for further</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>work</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>zarządzaniu</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>e-mail: j.patalas@iizp.uz.zgora.pl</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>