<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A COMPARISON OF SECURITY SAFEGUARD SELECTION METHODS</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Neubauer</surname></persName>
							<email>neubauer@securityresearch.ac.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Secure Business Austria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Favoritenstrasse 16</addrLine>
									<postCode>1040</postCode>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A COMPARISON OF SECURITY SAFEGUARD SELECTION METHODS</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Security</term>
					<term>Risk Management</term>
					<term>Economics</term>
					<term>Decision Support</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>IT security incidents pose a major threat to the efficient execution of corporate strategies and business processes. Although companies generally spend a lot of money on security companies are often not aware of their spending on security and even more important if these investments into security are effective. This paper provides decision makers with an overview of decision support techniques, describes pros and cons of these methodologies.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Companies are often not aware of their spending on security and even more important if the investments into security are effective. The definition of security safeguards is often a result of current needs or influ- enced by security problems that may go public. When seeking to select the most appropriate set of measures and, thus, the right level of security investments, de- cision makers are challenged by (i) having to concen- trate resources on value-generating and supplemen- tary business processes while (ii) having to consider multiple strategic objectives that are often conflicting as well as (iii) the cost-efficient usage of the available resources and interdependencies between the systems and (iv) a variety of potential technologies and po- tential systems. As a consequence security decisions provide only punctual solutions and are made without considering the costs and benefits of introducing the- ses measures. Accordingly, a variety of approaches have been introduced that aim to support decision makers in identifying the "right" investment candi- dates. This paper provides decision makers with an overview of common methods for the evaluation and selection of security safeguards and describes pros and cons of these methodologies. One major focus of this evaluation lies on identifying the method's capa- bilities in (i) considering business processes for align- ing expenditure to actual business needs and (ii) inte- grating multiple objectives in order to properly con- sider financial, technical and/or further types of ob- jectives. Thereby this paper supports decision makers in their decision which methods to choose when hav- ing to evaluate security investments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">COMPARISON</head><p>The Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP) developed by Saaty <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Saaty, 1980</ref>) is a tool for solving multi- criteria decision making problems and is based on the principles of hierarchy, pairwise comparison, and weight synthesizing for prioritizing criteria and the evaluation of alternatives. Specifically, the process consists of the following steps: Structuring a Hier- archy, Prioritizing the Criteria, Evaluating the Alter- natives, and Calculating the Global Priorities. The Analytic Hierarchy Process (AHP) is a widespread and easy to use decision support tool for evaluating different alternatives that can be applied to solve se- curity safeguard selection problems. Its strength is the analysis of the alternatives' properties in different categories, or in other words, the evaluation of alter- natives with respect to multiple objectives. The pair- wise comparison technique however requires (i) the direct comparability of alternatives and (ii) may re- sult in a major effort. As security safeguards are not limited to technical solutions but also include organi- zational measures and operational procedures, com- paring them directly may be problematic, e.g., com- paring a packet filtering firewall with a fire extin- guisher. Therefore, it may be beneficial not to use the AHP as a standalone tool for solving informa- tion security-related problems, but to integrate it with other methods. Regarding the effort, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Maiden (Maiden and Ncube, 1998)</ref> illustrates this fact by means of a case study of a project with about 130 requirements: because it would have required an estimated 42,000+ individual paired comparison scores, applying AHP was impossible in this and similar cases due to the time constraint involved. aggregated into a single scalar value used for the eval- uation, i.e., the threats and safeguards cannot be eval- uated subject to the attributes 'independently'. Also, SAEM does not consider the business processes and the safeguards' influence on them.</p><p>Another framework that takes multiple objectives into consideration when determining suitable secu- rity safeguards is the cost/benefit-based Security At- tribute Evaluation Method (SAEM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Butler, 2002)</ref>. As the risk assessment process is tasked with prioritiz- ing threats, a benefit assessment determines the safe- guard effectiveness, and a cost analysis determines the expenses associated with the security measures. The SAEM process involves the following four steps: Risk Assessment, Benefit Analysis, Coverage Analy- sis, and Security Technology Tradeoff Analysis. Un- like AHP, it was developed specifically for solving in- formation security evaluation problems and therefore particularly addresses security-related concepts such as threats and safeguard effectiveness. Multiobjectiv- ity is considered in the multiattribute risk assessment where threats are ranked according to their likeli- hood of occurrence and impact on attack outcome at- tributes. The resulting threat index values and the ef- fectiveness values of the security technologies under consideration are then used to calculate their risk re- duction impact. The coverage analysis ensures that no security gap is overlooked when arranging the safe- guard portfolio, and the tradeoff analysis compares the risk reduction impact and other benefits of secu- rity measures with their costs like implementation or maintenance costs. The SAEM approach is a very de- tailed and structured process to evaluate information security and safeguards. The risk assessment pro- cess ensures that specific threats are addressed, and the benefit and tradeoff analysis consider the multiob- jectivity of threat consequences and safeguard effec- tiveness. The normalization of threat and safeguard values also allows the concurrent usage of qualitative and quantitative data. But, as the SAEM method is quite detailed and extensive, it is also rather complex to conduct. Each phase requires relatively much work and, without automation of certain steps, this work can be quite tedious. Although this method allows the definition of multiple objectives, the outcome is still</p><p>The Central Computer and Telecommunications Agency (CCTA) Risk Analysis and Management Method (CRAMM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(InsightConsulting, 2007</ref>) is a commercial qualitative risk analysis methodology de- veloped by the UK government's Central Computer and Telecommunications Agency in full compliance with BS7799. CRAMM is divided into the three stages Asset Identification and Valuation, Threat and Vulnerability Assessment, and Countermeasure Se- lection and Recommendation. The CRAMM pro- cess includes the following steps: Assets, Threats, Vulnerabilities, Risks, Countermeasures, Implemen- tation, and Audit. The framework is intended for large governmental and commercial organizations. It pro- vides a structural method to identify relevant assets (arranged into asset groups), possible vulnerabilities, and threats, to combine them to risks that are mea- sured according to the assets' values and vulnerability and threat levels, and to recommend suitable counter- measures. The process is considered as rather com- plex and considerable experience is required in order to produce meaningful and correct results. There- fore, organizations often rely on external qualified CRAMM practitioners to conduct the analysis in- stead of letting internal analysts undergo the exten- sive training to gain the necessary expertise. This re- duces the organization's internal staff's involvement in the assessment phase and therefore also does not improve their insight into security matters. The out- come is often quite extensive and a full review may last up to several months. The framework neither of- fers the flexibility to customize it to the organizations characteristics, nor does it provide an evaluation of business process related issues. Grouping the assets into asset groups may also prove to be unfavorable, as all assets have their own properties and security re- quirements. And finally, CRAMM does not calculate economic indicators, such as implementation costs of the recommended safeguards and whether they fit into the security budget.</p><p>Operationally Critical Threat, Asset, and Vulner- ability Evaluation (OCTAVE) (CERT, 2007) is a risk- based strategic assessment and planning technique for security developed by the Carnegie Mellon Univer- sity. Essentially, the OCTAVE framework is a set of criteria containing guidelines and requirements for implementing process steps, instead of pre-specified techniques. These criteria must be fulfilled in or- der to correctly implement the OCTAVE framework.</p><p>Unlike other frameworks, the OCTAVE approach fo- cuses on organizational risks instead of technological ones and is structured into three phases: Build Asset- based Threat Profiles, Identify Infrastructure Vulner- abilities, and Develop Security Strategy and Plans. OCTAVE is quite different to CRAMM: On the one hand, the actual OCTAVE framework does not pro- vide a step by step procedure as CRAMM, but a set of criteria that has to be met to conform to the OC- TAVE methodology. This provides great adaptability and more flexibility than CRAMM to address specific organizational needs. For easier access, three specific application methods have been developed to choose from, suited for different sizes of organizations. On the other hand, it is self-directed, meaning that the OCTAVE methodology has to be wholly exercisable by the organization's internal staff in a workshop en- vironment, thus not relying on external experts. Fi- nally, OCTAVE is focused on organizational risks, whereas CRAMM concentrates more on technical is- sues, and OCTAVE generally does not take threat likelihood into consideration (except for OCTAVE S which provides basic means for including threat like- lihood in the evaluation).</p><p>While the risk assessment methodologies evaluate security technologies on their effectiveness to miti- gate risks, the POSeM framework deals with informa- tion security in a different way. The Process-Oriented Security Model (POSeM) framework developed at the University of Zürich by <ref type="bibr">Röhrig (Röhrig, 2002</ref>) is a methodology to define security requirements and to derive security measures by using process models as the basis for the analysis. In this proposal, the four security objectives confidentiality, integrity, availabil- ity, and accountability are used to measure the secu- rity levels of each process component (actor, artifact, activity), and suitable security measures are derived via rule bases. It takes into consideration that as- sets do not generate business value themselves, but participate in business processes that produce utility, and therefore the methodologies rely on business pro- cesses as the basis for their analysis. It also ignores specific harmful events (e.g., threats), but concentrate on eliciting security requirements and deriving appro- priate security measures. The POSeM approach con- sists of five steps: Definition of General Security Ob- jectives, SEPL Model, Consistency Analysis, Deriva- tion of Generic Security Measures, and an optional Implementation Phase. The strengths of the POSeM approach lie in the usage of business process mod- els as the basis for the security evaluation and the definition of organization specific rule sets for the consistency checks and safeguard derivation. Using process models seems to be a logical step in today's process-centered world. As processes are continually improved (or completely restructured with BPR tech- niques), the security status should be evaluated and improved in line with the business processes. Relying on the well established CIA properties also enhances the insight into security-related matters of processes, especially by assigning them to the individual process components (participant, data, activity). By defining organization-specific rules, the particularities of the organization and its main processes can be taken into consideration, thus reaching a high level of adaptabil- ity of the POSeM process. These rules can be spec- ified once and stored for further uses, which signif- icantly reduces the amount of time needed for the (re-)evaluation. And the formal description methods of SPEL, SMDL, and SCRL allow a high degree of automation, thus further reducing the workload. As emphasized by Röhrig, this framework is mainly in- tended to elicit the requirements for safeguards, but not to decide which specific safeguards to choose. As a matter of fact, it is not suited as a standalone deci- sion making method. The outcome of the evaluation is solely a list that is suitable for implementing the required security levels of the process components. This is underpinned by the fact that the economical factors of safeguards, namely their costs in monetary or time units, are completely neglected and only the technical aspect of security measures are evaluated. Furthermore, POSeM ignores any specific negative factors influencing business processes such as threats and vulnerabilities, which are integral parts of risk as- sessment practices. No harmful events (such as a viral infection of the information system) are considered and therefore no safeguards can be defined to counter that specific problem. This is a major disadvantage of a framework that is specifically designed to be a security evaluation process.</p><p>The CORAS Framework is a tool-supported and model-based risk analysis methodology, the result of the EU-funded CORAS project. The frame- work is founded on four pillars: Risk Documen- tation Framework, Risk Management Process, Inte- grated Risk Management Process and System Devel- opment Process, and Platform for Tool Inclusion. The CORAS framework that also applies UML for mod- eling security-related issues, is centered around a tra- ditional risk assessment process with asset, vulner- ability, threat identification and evaluation and safe- guard derivation. In order to model the risk entities, a UML profile has been developed. Unlike the other methods, CORAS incorporates techniques of other frameworks to realize its risk identification process (e.g., HAZard and OPerability study (HazOp) and Fault Tree Analysis). This ensures a thorough analy- sis of the problem, but also requires participants pro- ficient with these techniques to pick the most appro- priate. The main pillar of interest, the risk manage- ment process, is based on the Australian/New Zealand Standard AS/NZS 4360:1999: Risk Management and ISO/IEC 17799: 2000 Information technology -Code of practice for information security management. In contrast to specifying its own methods, the CORAS risk management process relies on techniques of other frameworks for each of the steps including HAZard and OPerability study (HazOp), Fault Tree Analy- sis (FTA), Failure Mode and Effect Criticality Analy- sis (FMECA), Markov analysis, and the CCTA Risk Analysis and Management Methodology (CRAMM). To provide a framework for modeling all risk-related aspects, a UML profile was developed to act as a graphical reference and communication method be- tween the different stakeholders. The risk manage- ment process consists of the following steps: Es- tablish Context, Identify Risks, Analyze Risks, Risk Evaluation, and Risk Treatment. The CORAS risk management process represents a holistic framework for the evaluation of information security of different application areas. It inherits all strengths and weak- nesses of the assessment methods it incorporates, and the graphical models are used for describing the tar- get system, its context, and all security features, and therefore provide a valuable insight into the subject and facilitates communication between the stakehold- ers. The combination of different analysis methods also reduces the individual weaknesses and therefore enhances the overall quality of the risk assessment outcome. This integration also poses a considerable drawback of the CORAS approach. As it is rec- ommended to rely on multiple methods in the same process step to get a more complete result, this also means an increased demand for time. Generally, the CORAS methodology is very time consuming, and the participants need experience in the multiple meth- ods to be able to select and apply them efficiently. needs and integrating multiple objectives. This com- parison reveals that all methodologies focus on cer- tain aspects of information security only and neglect others, thus not being able to provide a complete secu- rity evaluation of a business process and multiobjec- tive safeguard selection. The risk-based approaches take assets and threats into account and therefore con- sider specific risks in the analysis, but neglect busi- ness processes. POSeM in turn is process-based, but ignores specific threats and risks. None of these frameworks consider multiple criteria when evalu- ating the safeguards, except for AHP and SAEM. But AHP is not specifically developed to deal with security-related issues, thus lacking information secu- rity specific functionality. And SAEM can be consid- ered as a hybrid, including methods for multiobjective optimization and risk determination, but not as thor- ough as the other risk-based methods, and also lacks business process support.</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>Today many companies are not aware of their spending on security and if their investments into se- curity are effective. Decision makers are increas- ingly challenged by having to define an optimal set of security safeguards in line with the corporate busi- ness processes as well as multiple strategic objec- tives. This paper gave an overview of common meth- ods for the evaluation of security safeguards identi- fied the method's capabilities in considering business processes for aligning expenditure to actual business</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Security attribute evaluation method: a cost-benefit approach</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Butler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICSE &apos;02: Proceedings of the 24th International Conference on Software Engineering</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="240" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Insightconsulting</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.cramm.com" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2007-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Acquiring COTS software selection requirements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Maiden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ncube</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Software</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="56" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using process models to analyze health care security requirements</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Röhrig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference Advances in Infrastructure for e-Business, eEducation, e-Science, and e-Medicine on the Internet</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Italy</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Analytic Hierarchy Process</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Saaty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
