<Publication>
  <id>TUW-186227</id>
  <title>Information Requisition for Computer-Supported Medical Care</title>
  <abstractText>One indispensable precondition for designing a functional software product for the modeling and execution of a computerized clinical practice guideline (CPG) is the comprehensive investigation of the different user groups involved and the issues they encounter. This led us to conduct a comprehensive literature study about the tasks involved in modeling a CPG into a formal representation as well as about the information needs of caregivers, i.e., physicians and nurses, and last but not least the information needs of patients. We have assessed and categorized the above mentioned information in order to create a reliable starting point for the development of a functional software tool. evant guideline knowledge and to disambiguate this knowledge. For model-centric formalization the modeler formulates a conceptual model of a guideline without a direct relationship between the original text and the model. This modeling process involves steps like generating detailed data models of clinical concepts and fundamental parameters, specifying a logical and process structure of the CPG, and modeling the guideline knowledge by means of a flowchart-like graph.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Theresia</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Gschwandtner</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology Vienna</institution>
          <department>Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Katharina</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Kaiser</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Silvia</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Miksch</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>I. INTRODUCTION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>III. CLINICAL INFORMATION NEEDS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>II. INFORMATION NEEDS OF MODELERS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>IV. CONCLUSION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>C. PATIENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>