<Publication>
  <id>TUW-217971</id>
  <title>A Compound Approach for Interactive Visualization of Time-Oriented Data</title>
  <abstractText>Many real-world Visual Analytics applications involve time-oriented data. I am working in a research project related to this challenge where I am responsible for the interactive visualization part. My goal are interactive visualizations to explore such time-oriented data according to the user tasks while considering the structure of time. Time is composed of many granularities that are likely to have crucial influence on the formation of the data. The challenge is to integrate the granularities into a detailed compound view on the data, like the compound eye of insects integrates many images into one view. Other members of our team are experts in temporal data mining and user centered design. The goal is to combine our research topics to an integrated system that helps domain experts to get more insight from their time-oriented data. a natural context, like the change of seasons, they are usually regular , but granularities based on social context can also be irregular, e.g., easter time. They play an important role in many datasets from real-world applications, like customer data from shops. 1.2 Interactive Visualization Application domains where time-oriented-data occur include commerce , health care, public security, and others. These data are usually multivariate, resulting from heterogeneous data sources. In many cases, the structure of time has strongly influenced the events the data results from. The user tasks are complex and involve many abstract questions. By studying surveys of visualizations for time-oriented data like the one by Aigner [1], it becomes apparent that most current work at visualizing time-oriented data is focused on solving one or more of the pressing tasks, but most visualizations neglect the structure of time. In the following, this structure is discussed , as well as what we consider the most important research topics in developing interactive visualizations. User interaction is one of the most important elements of Info-Vis, or even the &quot;heart&quot; as Spence states [9]. User interaction is even more important in Visual Analytics, as studies like the one by Saraiya et al. [7] shows: users preferred inferior visualizations with interaction over superior static visualizations. The basic interactions in visualizations of time-oriented data are interval selections, like zooming and panning, but also others like detail on demand or brushing. Most interactions are not tailored particularly for time-oriented data. E.g., if a user analyzes a day and wants to see a day one month later, she often has to go forward 28-31 days, because the visualization is at day scale. It would be easier to just go forward one month, without having to think about details. If another user wants to zoom out to one month, he has not only to respect different month lengths, but also consider that the day viewed before might not be in the center of the month. Still, it is most likely the user wants to see the month that contains the day, from the first day to the last day. These examples show that it is important for interactive visualizations to respect the structure of time.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Tim</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Lammarsch</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Danube University Krems</institution>
          <department>Department of Information and Knowledge Engineering (ike)</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff1</id>
        </Affiliation>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff2</id>
          <department>METHOD OF RESEARCH</department>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[2]"/>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[3]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>1.2</level>
      <title>Interactive Visualization</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3.6</level>
      <title>[Computing Methodologies]: Computer Graphics-Methodology and Techniques; H.5.m [Information Sys- tems]: Information Interfaces And Presentation (e.g., HCI)- Miscellaneous</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1</level>
      <title>RESEARCH PROBLEMS AND STATE OF THE ART</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.3</level>
      <title>The Visualization Process</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>1.1</level>
      <title>The Structure of Time</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>RESEARCH QUESTIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>6</level>
      <title>CONCLUSION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>WORK PERFORMED SO FAR</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>NEXT WORKING STEPS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>