<Publication>
  <id>TUW-177140</id>
  <title>Testing Relativised Uniform Equivalence under Answer-Set Projection in the System cc⊤ ⋆</title>
  <abstractText>The system cc⊤ is a tool for testing correspondence between propo-sitional logic programs under the answer-set semantics with respect to different refined notions of program correspondence. The underlying methodology of cc⊤ is to reduce a given correspondence problem to the satisfiability problem of quantified propositional logic and to employ extant solvers for the latter language as back-end inference engines. In a previous version of cc⊤, the system was designed to test correspondence between programs based on relativised strong equivalence under answer-set projection. Such a setting generalises the standard notion of strong equivalence by taking the alphabet of the context programs as well as the projection of the compared answer sets to a set of designated output atoms into account. This paper outlines a newly added component of cc⊤ for testing similarly parameterised correspondence problems based on uniform equivalence. 1 Motivation and General Information An important issue in software development is to determine whether two encodings of a given problem are equivalent, i.e., whether they yield the same result on a given problem instance. Depending on the context of problem representations, different definitions of &quot;equivalence&quot; are useful and desirable. The system cc⊤ [1] (short for &quot;correspondence-checking tool&quot;) is devised as a checker for a broad range of different such comparison relations defined between disjunctive logic programs (DLPs) under the answer-set semantics [2]. In a previous version of cc⊤, the system was designed to test correspondence between logic programs based on relativised strong equivalence under answer-set projection. Such a setting generalises the standard notion of strong equivalence [3] by taking the alphabet of the context programs as well as the projection of the compared answer sets to a set of designated output atoms into account [4]. The latter feature ⋆</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Johannes</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Oetsch</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Technische Universität Wien</institution>
          <department>Institut für Informationssysteme</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Martina</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Seidl</lastName>
      <email>seidl@big.tuwien.ac.at</email>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff1</id>
          <institution>Technische Universität Wien</institution>
          <department>Institut für Softwaretechnik</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Hans</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Tompits</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Stefan</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Woltran</lastName>
      <email>woltran@dbai.tuwien.ac.at</email>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[2]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <level>2</level>
      <title>Background</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>3</level>
      <title>System Specifics</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>4</level>
      <title>cc⊤ on Stage</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <level>5</level>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>References</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>