<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Reconstructing Cross Cut Shredded Documents with a Genetic Algorithm with Solution Archive</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Benjamin</forename><surname>Biesinger</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Christian</forename><surname>Schauer</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Bin</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Günther</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Raidl</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Favoritenstrae 911/1861</addrLine>
									<postCode>1040</postCode>
									<settlement>Vienna</settlement>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Introduction</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Reconstructing Cross Cut Shredded Documents with a Genetic Algorithm with Solution Archive</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Results and Conclusions</head><p>We tested the proposed algorithm on several benchmark instances using different cutting patterns and compared the GA with and without the solution archive. By using the indexed trie as data structure, the memory consumption increased clearly too strongly after a relatively small number of iterations. Therefore the GA had to stop when it ran out of memory instead of when it converged, which produced worse results than the GA without archive. The linked trie variant, without causing additional run-time, consumed only one fourth of the memory. Unfortunately, even with this improvement the preliminary results were only on par with those generated by the GA without archive when using the same amount of time as stopping criterion. The reason is that the solution archive in this case is not able to fully compensate its overhead by saving the effort for re-evaluating duplicate solutions. However, when using a fixed number of iterations, the results of the GA with archive were better by far.</p><p>We conclude that on combinatorial optimization problems where the solution representation is not compact, using a solution archive with linked trie results  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>References 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Hu, B., Raidl, G.R.: An evolutionary algorithm with solution archives and bounding extension for the generalized minimum spanning tree problem. In: Proceedings of the 14th Annual Conference on Genetic and Evolutionary Computation (GECCO). pp. 393-400. ACM Press, Philadelphia, PA, USA (2012) 2. Perl, J., Diem, M., Kleber, F., Sablatnig, R.: Strip shredded document reconstruc- tion using optical character recognition. In: 4th International Conference on Imaging for Crime Detection and Prevention 2011 (ICDP 2011</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
