<Publication>
  <id>TUW-185441</id>
  <title>Measuring Shape Analysis Precision</title>
  <abstractText>Shape analysis is a static program analysis technique for discovering properties of heap-allocated data structures. It is crucial to finding software bugs or to verify high-level correctness properties. Various analyses have been introduced but their relation in terms of precision often remains unclear as different analyses use different abstractions of the heap. The aim of our work is to compare the precision of shape analyses. We propose a novel algorithm based on three-valued logic that extracts alias sets from shape graphs. Smaller sets are more precise and indicate a more precise underlying shape analysis. Using this metric, we experimentally compare-for the first time-the relative quality of the state-of-the-art graph-based shape analyses and make recommendations concerning the combination of analysis parameters. II. CONTRIBUTIONS We implemented multiple instances of state-of-the-art graph-based shape analyses for a subset of the C++ programming language and developed an algorithm based on three-valued logic that extracts alias information from shape graphs. Using this algorithm as a metric indicating the precision of the underlying shape analysis we are able to judge the effects of individual analysis parameters on runtime and precision of the analyses. In detail, the contributions address theory, practice, and assessment of shape analyses: A. THEORY</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Viktor</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Pavlu</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Institut für Computersprachen TU Wien Vienna</institution>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Markus</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Schordan</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>II. CONTRIBUTIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>I. INTRODUCTION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>B. PRACTICE</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>C. ASSESSMENT</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>May-Alias Set Sizes</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>IV. CONCLUSIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>