<Publication>
  <id>TUW-237297</id>
  <title>e-Learning as a solution for transition from high school to university:Challenges and possible solutions</title>
  <note>International Conference on e-Learning&apos;14 55</note>
  <abstractText>This paper is about the role of e-learning environments to support first year students of computer science. Our goal is to make their transition easier from high school to university learning as well as to introduce our students self-regulated learning step by step. Our results are based on our qualitative study with our students. We analyzed the interviews we carried out with them to identify challenges in the first semester program. In this paper we discussed some possible solutions with support of our e-learning environment we have already established. We know that we need to adapt our system to meet these challenges. We conclude our paper with our future work. INTRODUCTION Seen as a supporting electronic technology e-learning is well-established at several universities for several reasons: to support the lecturers to prepare their courses in a multimodal way, to support students to get all relevant information of a course asynchronously, to provide additional support to students by answering their questions and helping them in their assignments, to name a few. Additional features of creating time schedules, discussion groups and forums among participants, messaging mechanisms, grading and feedback possibilities, etc. make the teaching and learning easier to all stakeholders involved. Nevertheless the most e-learning systems do not provide enough support for learning from students&apos; individual point of view and see learners as &quot;deindividualized and demoted noncritical homogenous users&quot; [6, p.273]. In this paper we show that the opposite is the case, especially when considering first semester students of higher education. If it comes to introduce self-regulated learning, it is not only about the material provided for the students [6] or using ICT to improve assessment processes [8], it is about processes like scheduling, planning, and managing the learning activities, or assessment of one&apos;s knowledge and preparation for exams, etc. These are the factors for what we show in this paper evidence from our field study. Considering learning as an active, self-regulated, constructive, and situated process [4] [1] e-learning systems need to support learners in management and organization of learning activities, especially when the study requirements are unfamiliar, high (at least higher than expected), and not much individualized. One of the main goals of our paper is to show how to accompany &quot;novice&quot; learners in the first semester of a computer science university study to &quot;advanced beginners&quot; [3]. Our focus is on e-learning support to self-regulated learning. Since there are several definitions of e-learning, we want to clarify that we refer to the following definition: &quot;… all forms of electronic supported learning and teaching, which are procedural in character and aim to effect the construction of knowledge with reference to individual experience, practice and knowledge of the learner. Information and communication systems, whether networked or not, serve as specific media (specific in the sense elaborated previously) to implement the learning process.&quot; [6, p.274]. Self-regulation is based on &quot;students&apos; self-generated thoughts and behaviors that are systematically oriented toward the attainment of their learning goals&quot; [5, p.59]. This also means that students contribute actively to their learning goals and procedure. The main research question we deal with in this paper is: How can we apply e-learning mechanisms and systems to help students to transit from familiar learning structures and habits at high school to autonomous self-organized learning at a university? This is followed by other questions like: How can we support a newcomer at a university at all? What do we need to consider in a first year computer science (CS)</abstractText>
  <keywords>
    <string>E-Learning</string>
    <string>learners&apos; requirements</string>
    <string>higher education</string>
    <string>self-regulated learning</string>
  </keywords>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Hilda</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Tellioğlu</lastName>
      <affiliations/>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations/>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref6</string>
        <string>ref9</string>
        <string>ref4</string>
        <string>ref3</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>THE SETTING</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>METHODOLOGY</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>RESULTS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>Challenge of complexity caused by the density of the lectures and responsibilities:</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref2</string>
        <string>ref1</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref1</id>
      <referenceIdString>b0</referenceIdString>
      <source>How People Learn: Brain, Mind, Experience and School</source>
      <publisher>National Academic Press</publisher>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>J</string>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Bransford</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>A</string>
            <string>L</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Brown</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>R</string>
            <string>R</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Cocking</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <location>Washington</location>
      <publicationDateString>2000</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2000</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref2</id>
      <referenceIdString>b1</referenceIdString>
      <source>A 360-degree Evaluation Framework for Doctoral Programs</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Calatrava</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Moreno</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>M</string>
            <string>D C</string>
          </firstNames>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2014</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2014</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref3</id>
      <referenceIdString>b2</referenceIdString>
      <source>Mind Over Machine: The power of Human Intuition and Expertise in the Era of the Computer</source>
      <publisher>Free Press</publisher>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>H</string>
            <string>L</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Dreyfus</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>S</string>
            <string>E</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Dreyfus</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <location>New York</location>
      <publicationDateString>1986</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1986</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref4</id>
      <referenceIdString>b3</referenceIdString>
      <title>Constructivism: New Implications for Instructional Technology</title>
      <source>Constructivism and the Technology of Instruction: A Conversation. Hillsdale</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>T</string>
            <string>M</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Duffy</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
            <string>H</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Jonassen</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <pageFrom>1</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>16</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>1992</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>1992</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref5</id>
      <referenceIdString>b4</referenceIdString>
      <title>Self-Regulation and Learning</title>
      <source>Handbook of Psychology. Part Two: Cognitive Contributions to Learning, Development, and Instruction</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
            <string>H</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Schunk</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>B</string>
            <string>J</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Zimmerman</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <pageFrom>59</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>78</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2003</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2003</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref6</id>
      <referenceIdString>b5</referenceIdString>
      <title>Is eLearning the Solution for Individual Learning</title>
      <source>Electronic Journal of e-Learning</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Tavangarian</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>M</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Leypold</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>K</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Nölting</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>M</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Röser</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Voigt</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <pageFrom>273</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>280</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2004</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2004</publicationYear>
      <type>j</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref7</id>
      <referenceIdString>b6</referenceIdString>
      <source>Bericht zur Spezialauswertung: Zeugnisse zu den Lehrveranstaltungen der Studieneingangs-und Orientierungsphase (StEOP) der</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>Sh</string>
            <string>M</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Tauböck</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2014</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2014</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref8</id>
      <referenceIdString>b7</referenceIdString>
      <source>Bachelorstudien Informatik für die Beginnkohorten der Wintersemester 2011-2012 an der TU Wien, Stabstelle Studienbezogene Daten</source>
      <authors/>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref9</id>
      <referenceIdString>b8</referenceIdString>
      <title>Modes of classroom assessment in computer science</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the 12th International Conference on Computer Systems and Technologies, CompSysTech&apos;11</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>H</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Tellioğlu</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <pageFrom>546</pageFrom>
      <pageTo>551</pageTo>
      <publicationDateString>2017-06-16</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2017</publicationYear>
      <publicationMonth>06</publicationMonth>
      <publicationDay>16</publicationDay>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
  </references>
</Publication>