<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Justyna Patalas-Maliszewska Dr., University of Zielona Góra, Poland/</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>The author&apos;s software system for planning and selection of personnel in SME Abstract: The strategic management of intellectual capital involves rethinking how the companies creates value from a knowledge -centric perspective and redesigning and orchestrating the role of staff knowledge in the firm&apos;s strategy. This paper presents the author&apos;s software system for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge. This software is a computer implementation of the method for planning and selection of personnel in SME. information systems that support knowledge management in SMEs can give guarantees a constant competitive advantage in the market. Keywords: intellectual capital, strategic knowledge management</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The advantage of a company in the SME sector (small and medium sizes enterprises) is determined by effectiveness and the extent of the knowledge-workers' involvement. The role of intellectual capital management consists in striving to increase the share of immaterial resources (at the costs of the material ones) in the generated products, services, and the total market value of an organization ( <ref type="bibr">Król and Ludwiczyński, 2007</ref>).</p><p>The article presents the description of strategic knowledge resources in companies and author's method for plannig and selection of personnel in SME (see chapter 2). In the third chapter the author's software sys- tem for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge is presented on example of the decision-making situation in which an innovative SME is considering the employ- ment of a new m-th employee. The summary shows the directions of further work.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Author's method for planning and selection of strategic knowledge resources in SME</head><p>To manage of intellectual capital more systematically, the firm must devise an agenda for transforming from an organisation simply comprising knowledge able individuals to a knowledge-focused organisation that stewards the creation and sharing of knowledge within and across internal business function and that orchestrates the flow of know-how to and from external firms.</p><p>While resources are important to the performance of a firm, according to a resource-based view, whether or not an organization gains a competitive advantage and any associated returns, depends on the strategic planning used to leverage those resources ( <ref type="bibr">Chrisman et al., 2003)</ref>; <ref type="bibr">(McGrath and MacMillan, 2000</ref>).</p><p>The need to describe a strategic-knowledge resource was motivated by the concept of resource management <ref type="bibr">(Sirmon and Hitt, 2003)</ref> as well as competence manage- ment ( <ref type="bibr">Berio and Harzallah, 2005</ref>)-see <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref>:</p><p>Many studies have focused on knowledge manage- ment strategies and methodologies from an organizational perspective ( <ref type="bibr">Barthelme et al., 1998)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">(Basu, 1998)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">(Carayannis, 1998)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">(Drew, 1999</ref>). Many useful studies on the development of information sharing systems and col- laborative tools to support intra-organizational processes and teamwork also exist <ref type="bibr">(Chen and Liang, 1999</ref>). However, both the methodology and software system functionality for knowledge management are highly de- pendent on the process characteristics and the knowledge involved.</p><p>The competitive advantage of companies, especially SMEs, decide to increasingly knowledge and innovation potential. Knowledge is a broad concept, embracing both the knowledge formalized (explicit) and non-formal knowledge (hidden). Looking at the relationship between data, information, management information and knowledge <ref type="bibr">(Senn, 1990)</ref> should be regarded knowledge as a strategic resource company. Application of The next chapter presents the author's software sys- tem for facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge, which considers all elements of the presented method.</p><p>Strategic Knowledge Resource: personnel SME usefulness function Wnm for the m-th employee in the SME: Wnm = f1(GK) +f2(PK) +f3(A) +f4(E) + f5(P) + f6(C) + f7(R),</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">The author's software system for</head><p>facilitating decision making at a strategic level in terms of the profitability of investment in staff knowledge -example of using where: n, m∈ N, • f1(GK) -the general knowledge function for the m-th employee in SME, • f2(PK) -the professional knowledge function for the m-th em- ployee in SME, • f3(A) -the professional abilities function for the m-th employee in SME, • f4(E) -the experience function for the m-th employee in SME, • f5(P) -the patents function for the m-th employee in SME, • f6(C) -the clients function for the m-th employee in SME, • f7(R) -the m-th employee's personality in an SME.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 1 Definition of strategic-knowledge resources in</head><p>SMEs So, the following personnel SME usefulness function Wnm for the m-th employee in the SME is proposed:</p><p>The decision regarding the selection of an appropriate employee requires the company management to assess the efficiency of this investment. The application of the model makes it possible to obtain a forecast of the value of the strategic knowledge resources within a given or- ganisation. The decision-making situation, in which an innovative SME is considering the employment of the m-th employee, is presented in the diagram: Wnm = f1(GK) +f2(PK) +f3(A) +f4(E) + f5(P) + f6(C) + f7(R), where: n, m∈ N,</p><p>The two databases created on the basis of the replies of respondents in a</p><p>The linear form of this function Wnm is chosen because all elements are independent and equally important to assess the effectiveness and efficiency of investment in knowledge. It is possible to receive indispensable data for account of value personnel usefulness function from com- panies belonged to reference model of SMEs (Patalas- Maliszewska, 2009) by interview in each enterprise. Each employee should complete the questionnaire. On the basis of an algorithm for testing solutions for each em- ployee it is possible to receive a specific value of the per- sonnel usefulness function and each of the parameters of this function.</p><p>questionnaire-based survey, the experiences of 10 Polish SMEs:</p><p>• The decision-making model for the assessment of the efficiency of the selection of the m-th employee for an SME:</p><p>• Built on the basis of a defined database with the use of GMDH, • Combined selected indicators.</p><p>Is an employee being sought who guarantees that the SME may gain the A four-element method for the planning and selection of strategic knowledge resources in SME has been built. The four elements are:</p><p>• A reference model of an SME-sector company,</p><p>• The value of the personnel usefulness function desired values of the qualification criteria for an innovative company?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 1:</head><p>The implementation of data which is characteristic for an SME-sector for each m-th employee in SME • The qualifying criteria in an innovative company, • An algorithm which will enable the connection of company in a computer program (consistent with the reference model) the value of strategic resources of knowledge to the value of the qualifying criteria for an innova- tive company -GMDH.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 2:</head><p>The application of a defined decision-making model with use of the imple- mented data of a company with the aid of a computer program</p><p>The method was created on the basis of methods for the assessment of capital value and on the characteristics of innovative companies. It combines available knowl- edge gained from literature, and experiences of SMEs which have the potential for innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 3:</head><p>The forecasting of the value of strategic knowledge resources in an innova- tive SME (the value of personnel usefulness function); depending on the defined values of the innovation characteristics</p><p>The method allows for making an assessment of the future value of the decision about the selection of an em- ployee in the relation to increasing innovation in a SME- sector company.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 4:</head><p>Conducting an interview with a potential employee using the program - establishing the current value of the value of personnel usefulness function</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 5:</head><p>The comparison of the forecasted value of a strategic resource of knowl- edge with its current value</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stage 6:</head><p>The recommendation of the m-th employee (in terms of the smallest discrepancy between the forecasted value of a strategic resource of knowledge with its current value) <ref type="figure">Fig. 2</ref> The decision-making situation in which an innovative SME is considering the employment of a new m-th employee</p><p>The decision-making situation of the SME sector has been presented; this decides on the employment of new employees in sales. Also the author has described the example of the company A2, which is looking for an em- ployee to the fill the position of 'regional assistant'. The company expects to retain its current level of innovation. Using the proposed system, it is possible to check to see whether the company complies with the specified refer- ence model. A potential new employee selects actions that will be performed in the company. The developed reference model will help companies to determine the work place for a new employee.</p><p>Through the use of the tool known as the system to sup- port decision making at the strategic level with regards to the assessment of knowledge in an innovative SME, which is the implementation of the method for planning and selection of personnel in SME, the following informa- tion was produced:</p><p>• For m4 -Regional Assistant:  Using the the author's software system, the actual value of the personnel usefulness function for a new employee is checked (see <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref>): <ref type="figure">Fig. 4</ref> Example of using the author's software system thodical and uniformity, fairness and impartiality, profes- sionalism. <ref type="figure">Fig. 6</ref> Example of using the author's software system</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head><p>Stage 5:</p><p>Then we compare the actual value of the personnel use- fulness function with the expected new employee. If these values are similar, it is assumed that the employment of the employee will allow us to maintain the current level of innovation within the company.</p><p>The actual value of the function: Wm4 = 19</p><p>The forecast value of the function: The company can decide to recruit new employees for the position of 'Regional assistant' because the predicted value of the personnel usefulness function for the new employee is in line with the actual value of the function, which would allow the company to maintain a certain level of innovation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion and direction for further work</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Strategic Knowledge Resource in SMEs: unique resources of individual employees which allow SMEs to gain a sustainable competitive advantage</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Database of values of the personnel usefulness function: Wnm for each m-th employee in area Fn n,m∈N, • Database of the values of the characteristics of innovation: xi in SME for k-companies i,k∈N</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 Example of using the author's software system</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>where X7 -number of employees with scientific degrees, X13 -the number of purchased and used licenses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3 Example of using the author's software system</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>8323X7X13 = 19,6231 for X7 -number of employees with scientific degrees -X7 = 2, X13 -the number of purchased and used licenses -X13 = 1</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
