<Publication>
  <id>TUW-168222</id>
  <title>Optimization of communication by analyzing the interlocutor&apos;s wording</title>
  <abstractText>Recent research results on communication science mention a relation between the inter-locutor&apos;s perceptional preferences, his or her mental representations and his or her choice of expressions. However, there is not any tool for analyzing such. In my research I combined lexical with computational linguistic methods to develop a software prototype that is able to analyze text on the usage of perceptional expressions. This analyzing tool can help to identify the interlocutor&apos;s perceptional preference for easier meeting his or her way of thinking and thereby facilitate the understanding. Still, for the German language, not much research on the relation between an individual&apos;s perceptional preference and his or her language use has been done yet. To be able to go deeper into that idea, (1) a lexical corpus of perceptional expressions and (2) a software tool that automatically filters those expressions from a text are needed. Those two steps shall be explained in this abstract.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Gudrun</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Kellner</lastName>
      <email>Email: kellner@ec.tuwien.ac.at</email>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology Vienna</institution>
          <department>Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>II. A LEXICAL CORPUS OF PERCEPTIONAL EXPRESSIONS</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>I. INTRODUCTION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>REFERENCES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>IV. FURTHER RESEARCH</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references/>
</Publication>