<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 C:\Users\Angela\git\grobid\grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.5-dummy" ident="GROBID" when="2017-12-29T00:16+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Integration of Text and Audio Features for Genre Classification in Music Information Retrieval</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Neumayer</surname></persName>
							<email>{neumayer,rauber}@ifs.tuwien.ac.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Rauber</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Vienna University of Technology</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Integration of Text and Audio Features for Genre Classification in Music Information Retrieval</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Multimedia content can be described in versatile ways as its essence is not limited to one view. For music data these multiple views could be a song&apos;s audio features as well as its lyrics. Both of these modalities have their advantages as text may be easier to search in and could cover more of the &apos;content semantics&apos; of a song, while omitting other types of semantic categorisation. (Psycho)acoustic feature sets, on the other hand, provide the means to identify tracks that &apos;sound simi-lar&apos; while less supporting other kinds of semantic categorisation. Those discerning characteristics of different feature sets meet users&apos; differing information needs. We will explain the nature of text and audio feature sets which describe the same audio tracks. Moreover, we will propose the use of textual data on top of low level audio features for music genre classification. Further, we will show the impact of different combinations of audio features and textual features based on content words.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>The large-scale adoption of new business models for digital audio material is hap- pening already. What many content providers and online music vendors are still missing are appropriate means of presenting their media to their users according to different information needs. Amazon 1 or last.fm 2 have shown the potential of recommendation engines based on the mining of transactional data.</p><p>It further is an intrinsic need for every Music Information Retrieval system to include not only recommendation or playlist generation engines, but also pos- sibilities for searching and browsing. Music Information Retrieval has made huge progress in terms of devising sophisticated descriptors for the acoustic content of music. Research in this direction facilitates numerous content-based search scenarios, such as query by humming, or organisation tasks, such as genre classi- fication, playlist generation, and browsing access by perceived sound similarity.</p><p>Song lyrics cover semantic information about a song's contents on a level that could never be covered by audio features only. Many users may rather be interested in songs that cover similar topics than sound alike. Some musical genres, such as e.g. Christmas candles, can only be detected by including textual features, as they occur across many different musical genres and the definition of the genre itself is rather done on a topic level.</p><p>We thus combine both textual as well as audio information for music genre classification, i.e. automatically assigning musical genres to tracks based on audio features as well as content words in song lyrics.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organised as follows. Section 2 provides a brief overview of related work. This is followed by a description of our classification experiments in Section 3, as well as outlook on current work in Section 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Related Work</head><p>The area of Music Information Retrieval has been heavily researched, particu- larly focusing on audio feature extraction. First experiments with content-based Music Information Retrieval were reported in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> as well as <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[6]</ref>, the focus be- ing on automatic genre classification of music. In this paper we use a modified version of the Rhythm Patterns features, previously used within the SOMeJB system <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>. Based on that feature set, <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> shows that the Statistical Spectrum Descriptors yield relatively good results at a manageable dimensionality.</p><p>A sophisticated semantic and structural analysis including language identi- fication of songs based on lyrics is conducted in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. Artist similarity based on song lyrics is performed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, pointing out that similarity retrieval using lyrics is inferior to acoustic similarity. It is also suggested that a combination of lyrics and acoustic similarity could improve results, further motivating the research reported in this paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Experiments</head><p>Due to the lack of public benchmark corpora, we created a parallel corpus of audio and song lyrics files of a music collection of 9.758 titles organised into 41 genres. Class sizes ranged from only a few songs for the 'Classical' genre to about 1.900 songs for 'Punk Rock'. In order to utilise the information contained in music for genre classification, we describe sets of audio features derived from the waveform of audio tracks as well as the bag-of-word features for song lyrics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Audio Features</head><p>Three features were computed from audio tracks in standard PCM format with 44.1 kHz sampling frequency (e.g. decoded MP3 files). Rythm Patterns (RP) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[5]</ref>, also called Fluctuation Patterns, denote a matrix representation of fluctuations on critical bands (parts of it describe rhythm in the narrow sense), resulting in a 1.440 dimensional feature space. Statistical Spectrum Descriptors <ref type="bibr">(SSDs, 168</ref> dimensions) are statistical moments derived from a psycho-acoustically trans- formed spectrogram <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Rhythm Histograms (RH, 60 dimensions) are calculated as the sums of the magnitudes of each modulation frequency bin of all 24 critical bands.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Lyrics Features</head><p>For every piece of music, three lyrics portals were accessed, using artist name and track title as queries. If the results from lyrc.com.ar were of reasonable size, these lyrics were assigned to the track. If lyrc.com.ar fails, sing365lyrics.com will be checked for validity, then oldielyrics.com. All lyrics were processed using the bag-of-words model and weighted by tfidf information. Feature selection was done via document frequency thresholding, i.e. the omittance of terms that occur in a very high or very low number of documents. For the matrices used for the experiments terms occurring in more than half of the documents were omitted, the lower threshold was then adjusted to meet the desired dimensionality. Downscaling was performed to different di- mensionalities matching the dimensionalities of the audio feature spaces. <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">Table 1</ref> shows classification accuracies for a set of experiments based on audio and lyrics features as well as combinations thereof. Experiments were performed by Weka's implementation of Support Vector Machines for ten-fold stratified cross validation. Results shown are the macro averaged classification accuracies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Classification Results</head><p>Results show that a combination of lyrics and audio features improves over- all classification performance. The best results were achieved by the 'LYRICS + RP' setting (C3), closely followed by the 'LYRICS + SSD' experiment (C2). The higher-dimensional the data for the lyrics experiments is, the higher is its classification accuracy, implying that there is even more discriminating informa- tion contained in lyrics (see experiments L1 -L4), which is not covered in this context because of the limitations of the simple concatenation approach. For combination experiments (C1 -C3) we use balanced combinations of features, i.e. the dimensionality of the lyrics component always equals the dimensionality of the audio feature component.</p><p>For statistical significance testing we used a paired T-test for a significance level of α = .05. is a strong basis for a classifier. Hence a classifier based on differing numbers of lyrics than audio features, e.g. more dimensions in the lyrics than in the audio space, might further improve classification accuracy. Yet, by combining lyrics and audio (C2) the same performance was achieved at a fraction of the dimensionality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Conclusions and Future Work</head><p>We showed that the combination of multi-modal features for information re- trieval increases classification accuracy. Future work will deal with better means of combining classification results. Ensemble methods might prove useful, over- coming the limitation of implicit feature weighting encountered in the current setting. Additionally, stylistic features for text genre classification are currently being integrated.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="true"><head>Table 1 . Classification accuracies for different types and combinations of audio features and features based on lyrics. The experiments A1 -A3 denote audio-only, L1 -L4 lyrics-only, and C1 -C3 features combined from audio and lyrics feature sets. The</head><label>1</label><figDesc>type column shows the types of feature sets used, dimensionality notes the resulting dimensionality of the data.</figDesc><table>Name Type 
Dimensionality Classification Accuracy 
A1 RH. 
60 
.3100 
A2 SSD. 
168 
.4168 
A3 RP. 
1440 
.4128 
L1 LYRICS 
60 
.2451 
L2 LYRICS 
168 
.3204 
L3 LYRICS 
1440 
.4445 
L4 LYRICS 
3000 
.4708 
C1 LYRICS + RH 
120 
.3268 
C2 LYRICS + SSD 
336 
.4817 
C3 LYRICS + RP 
2880 
.4841 

</table></figure>

			<note place="foot" n="1"> http://www.amazon.com 2 http://www.last.fm</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An overview of audio information retrieval</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jonathan</forename><surname>Foote</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Multimedia Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluation of feature extractors and psychoacoustic transformations for music genre classification</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Thomas</forename><surname>Lidy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Rauber</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Sixth International Conference on Music Information Retrieval (ISMIR 2005)</title>
		<meeting>the Sixth International Conference on Music Information Retrieval (ISMIR 2005)<address><addrLine>London, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="34" to="41" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Semantic analysis of song lyrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Beth</forename><surname>Logan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andrew</forename><surname>Kositsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pedro</forename><surname>Moreno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 2004 IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo, ICME</title>
		<meeting>the 2004 IEEE International Conference on Multimedia and Expo, ICME<address><addrLine>Taipei, Taiwan</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004-06-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Jose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Alvaro</forename><surname>Mahedero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Pedro</forename><surname>Martínez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Markus</forename><surname>Cano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Koppenberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Natural language processing of lyrics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Fabien</forename><surname>Gouyon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MULTIMEDIA &apos;05: Proceedings of the 13th annual ACM international conference on Multimedia</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="478" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using psycho-acoustic models and self-organizing maps to create a hierarchical structuring of music by musical styles</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Andreas</forename><surname>Rauber</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Elias</forename><surname>Pampalk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Dieter</forename><surname>Merkl</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 3rd International Symposium on Music Information Retrieval</title>
		<meeting>the 3rd International Symposium on Music Information Retrieval<address><addrLine>Paris, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="80" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Marsyas: A framework for audio analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">George</forename><surname>Tzanetakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Perry</forename><surname>Cook</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Organized Sound</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">30</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
