<Publication>
  <id>TUW-185321</id>
  <title>Bridging Semantic Heterogeneities in Open Source Software Development Projects with Semantic Web Technologies</title>
  <abstractText>The semantic heterogeneity of Open Source Software (OSS) development projects comes from the using of different tools and models by the various stakeholders. These differences make the process of integration become difficult, since the project managers should recognize the different structure of the tools and models for analyzing the state of the projects. This manual analysis is costly and error prone. In this work we propose a semantic web technology approach to bridge these semantic heterogeneities, by using engineering knowledge base (EKB). The EKB enables mapping between local and domain ontology layers to allow querying the local tool knowledge using the domain-level knowledge and syntax. We empirically evaluate the feasibility of an EKB-based project monitoring system based on real-world data. to model the project/domain knowledge that are used and understood by all stakeholders and tools. Concepts in this model are then mapped to local tool data models, which model common domain concepts in different ways. Based on this mapping queries to the domain knowledge can be resolved via the mappings by local tool data queries. We will check the feasibility of querying the on-tologies in EKB written in SPARQL 1 format with the case from an open source project. The major result is the easier definition of queries on project data originating from heterogeneous background.</abstractText>
  <keywords/>
  <authors>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Wikan</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Danar</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation>
          <id>aff0</id>
          <institution>Vienna University of Technology Vienna</institution>
          <department>Institute of Software Technology and Interactive Systems</department>
          <country>Austria</country>
          <countryCode>AT</countryCode>
        </Affiliation>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Sunindyo</string>
      </firstNames>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
    <Author>
      <firstNames>
        <string>Stefan</string>
      </firstNames>
      <lastName>Biffl</lastName>
      <affiliations>
        <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
      </affiliations>
    </Author>
  </authors>
  <affiliations>
    <Affiliation reference="/Publication[1]/authors[1]/Author[1]/affiliations[1]/Affiliation[1]"/>
  </affiliations>
  <sections>
    <Section>
      <title>II. RESEARCH ISSUES</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>I. INTRODUCTION</title>
      <referenceIds>
        <string>ref1</string>
      </referenceIds>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>III. EVALUATION</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
    <Section>
      <title>IV. CONCLUSION AND FUTURE WORK</title>
      <referenceIds/>
      <referenceCitations/>
    </Section>
  </sections>
  <citationContexts/>
  <references>
    <Reference>
      <id>ref1</id>
      <referenceIdString>b0</referenceIdString>
      <title>Integrating Production Automation Expert Knowledge Across Engineering Stakeholder Domains</title>
      <source>Proceedings of the 2010 International Conference on Complex, Intelligent and Software Intensive Systems (to be published)</source>
      <authors>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>T</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Moser</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>S</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Biffl</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>W</string>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Sunindyo</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
        <ReferenceAuthor>
          <firstNames>
            <string>D</string>
          </firstNames>
          <lastName>Winkler</lastName>
        </ReferenceAuthor>
      </authors>
      <publicationDateString>2010</publicationDateString>
      <publicationYear>2010</publicationYear>
      <type>m</type>
      <publication reference="/Publication[1]"/>
    </Reference>
  </references>
</Publication>